<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Master Broughtons letters, especially his last pamphlet to and against  the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury, about Sheol and Hades, for the descent into Hell, answered in their kind</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3864</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851414</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 309:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Master Broughtons letters, especially his last pamphlet to and against  the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury, about Sheol and Hades, for the descent into Hell, answered in their kind</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by [F. Kingston for] Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Broughton, Hugh.  An explication of the article peri tou katelthein eis haidou.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ [chi]² .</note>
                  <note>With a final bifolium comparing Broughton's pronouncements with those of Miles Gloriosus; recto, column 1, line 3 up has "sayd".</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An answer fitting Broughtons slaunderous letters.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612. --  Explication of the article peri tou katelthein eis haidou --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Descent into hell --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16685:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16685:1"/>
            <p>MASTER BROVGHTONS LETTERS, <hi>Eſpecially his laſt Pamphlet to and againſt</hi> the <hi>Lord Archbiſhop</hi> of Canterbury, about <hi>Sheol</hi> and <hi>Hades,</hi> for the deſcent into <hi>Hell,</hi> anſwered in their kind.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALME. 85.</bibl> I ſaid vnto the fooles, Deale not ſo madly.</q>
            <q>Quicquid amas, cupias non placuiſſe nimis.
<bibl>Martial.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe, 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16685:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16685:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xpect not (gentle Reader) any matter of great weight and ſubſtance in this anſwer, the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellers</hi> defence (as he cals it) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nought elſe in ballance of ſound iudgement, but the fume of enuie, and the fome of vanitie: only accept it as <hi>a rod for a fooles backe,</hi> I feare <hi>incorrigible, nam ſenex Pſittacus non capit ferulam:</hi> who though he be brayed in a morter, will ſtill continue to bray like himſelfe. If thou thinkeſt it too bitter, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his <hi>Libell</hi> and this anſwere; the reuerend <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> whom with his foule mouthed ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders he defileth, and himſelf a vainglorious <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> a fugitiue abroad, a ſchiſmatike at home, a tormentor of ſoules with myſticall riddles, a cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous trumpetor of his owne praiſes, and ſo iudge of both. Some, I know, haue ſaid, he is
<pb facs="tcp:16685:3"/> halfe mad that ſhould anſwere him; <hi>a ſmooth co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for idlenes,</hi> and a goodly couer to ſhadow <hi>their ingratitude,</hi> who ſerue a maſter for fee, not loue, and care not how he is abuſed, ſo they be exalted. I ſay with <hi>Dauid, Adhuc vilior fiam pluſquam factus ſum,</hi> and, as it is, haue done it: if thou approue it, I glorie not: if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, I care not. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16685:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PROV. 14. 3.</bibl>
               <q>In the mouth of a foole is the rod of pride.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a fantaſtical fellow in <hi>Dion</hi> much-what of your humour, <hi>Maſter Broughton,</hi> who was fully perſwaded, that, becauſe he had maried <hi>Tully</hi> his widow, of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie<note place="margin">Dion Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> he ſhould proue <hi>ſummus Orator;</hi> or in that he had once ſate in <hi>Caeſars</hi> chaire, he muſt needes become <hi>ſummus Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor:</hi> ſuch is your conceit, as appeareth by your manifold malepart letters to her <hi>Maiestie,</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> and the late <hi>L. Treaſurer,</hi> that be like becauſe a <hi>Iew</hi> once ſaluted you with an epiſtle (as you faigne) therefore you are the only <hi>Hebrician,</hi> and in that your armes are the three <hi>Owles, Athens</hi> fowles, forſooth, therefore you are the onely <hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> in the world, and which are your owne words, by <hi>Heroaldie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. ad Theſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>a great gentleman, and therefore no meane place muſt ſerue your turne.</hi> This conceit of yours, whetted with ſome ſmall learning, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially edged with naturall pride, hath made your tongue ſo keene, and your ſtile ſo ſharpe, that neither ſpares to wound whom your fancie miſliketh. Aboue all others you haue choſen the moſt <hi>Reuerend father the L. Archbiſhop of Canterbury</hi> to launce and cut therewith, <note n="*" place="margin">Ep. ad eun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>reioycing,</hi> as you ſay, <hi>to haue ſo high a perſonage to worke vpon,</hi> threatning in your letters to a <hi>Doctor of Diuinitie, to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ad D. Stoll.</note> 
                  <hi>ſet either his Graces fame, or your owne paſt cure.</hi> I know that <hi>Accius</hi> is reported to haue cut through a whetſtone with a raſor (it may<note place="margin">Liuy.</note> bee he deſerues the whetſtone that records the ſtorie) yet that was a miracle, and a greater would it be accounted by him who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16685:4"/> knowes you both, that your pen, <hi>Sir Hugh,</hi> made of a gooſe quil, ſhould any way pearce, much leſſe wound, the impenetrable fame of a Prelate, ſo learned, ſo graue and vertuous. Whom, if you knew how little your virule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t letters (parbreakt from a poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonfull ſtomacke, ingorged with impudent lies, belching forth inſolent and vnſauourie challenges) did affect or moue, were you not paſt all ſhame, you would haue done with them; as that <hi>Emperour</hi> did with his <hi>Aiax,</hi> long ſince haue put them to the<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et. Aug.</note> ſpunge: or, as it ſeemeth, being void of all patience, with that rayling Poet, when he ſaw his <hi>Inuectiues</hi> nothing moued his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, ſlipt his neck into an halter, &amp; made a rafter his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed: and ſo, as the Poet ſaid, haue made of your ſelfe one long<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lut. diſt. adul.</note> letter, to ſee ſo ſmall effect of your lying letters. Wherefore if you expect his <hi>Graces</hi> owne anſwere to your <hi>querulous Libels,</hi> for all your much pretended learning, you ſhew your ſelfe, in that, an idiot, to thinke that either he ſhould bee ſo idle in that high place, being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: or ſo prodigall of precious<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phocles.</note> time, as to waſte good houres in anſwering ſuch vaine follies, or ſo careleſſe of his honour, as to ſtoope the billing of ſuch filthie garbage: yea ſo much he pities your madnes, (being acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith from your ſubſizerſhip in <hi>Trinitie Colledge</hi>) that when ſome ſonnes of <hi>Zeruiah,</hi> in zeale of his high calling, offered<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am. 16.</note> themſelues to throttle this <hi>Shemei</hi> and hot-tongued curre, his anſwer was to them with <hi>Seneca, Quibuſdam canibus innatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, vt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. de rem. fort.</note> 
                  <hi>non pro feritate, ſed pro conſuetudine latrent:</hi> It is cuſtome, not curſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which makes him barke. Wherein, vnder correction, his <hi>Grace</hi> is deceiued in you: for a dog not wormed while he is yong, will in time proue mad: your worme from your youth hath been a proud conceit of your ſelf, which, being no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſhed vnder your tongue ſo long, makes it now runne riot. It is to late to worme you, and preuent your madding, but time enough to file your teeth, or muzzle you, to keepe you from biting. And this haue I taken vpon me to doe, the weakeſt of many, who would faine haue been vpon you, yet ſtrong enough to grapple with <hi>Hugh Broughton, a man of ſuch rare wants and ſingular imperfections.</hi> How the <hi>Reuerend Archbiſhop</hi> will like it I know not, whoſe replie, being moued thereunto, hath bin that of <hi>Salomons, Anſwer not a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u. 26. 4.</note>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16685:4"/> 
                  <hi>foole according to his follie, leaſt thou alſo be like him.</hi> All one with that of <hi>Socrates,</hi> fitting, in metaphore, you more aptly: <hi>If an Aſſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diog laert.</note> 
                  <hi>kicke me, ſhall I kicke him againe?</hi> Notwithſtanding I take my ſelfe, being both a member of that Church, whereof his <hi>Grace</hi> next vnder her <hi>Maiestie,</hi> hath chief gouernment, &amp; alſo an attendant on him, ingaged to him by ſome fauours, bound in conſcience to ſpend a few ſpare houres of vacant time, in anſwering thoſe ſaucie letters, ſlanderous reproches, and ſcandalous imputations of a <hi>conceited, malecontented runnagate,</hi> ſuch a one whom <hi>S. Peter</hi> and <hi>Iude</hi> haue liuely deſcribed <hi>Preſumptuous, ſtanding in his owne</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. Iud. verſ. 8. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>conceit, a wandring ſtarre, a raging waue of the ſea foming out his owne ſhame, and ſpeaking euill of them which are in authoritie.</hi> Which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging madnes, had it kept it ſelfe in inke vnder ſeale, ſilence had been the beſt anſwere, and your papers, <hi>Sir Pamphletor,</hi> might haue made fit ſacrifices for <hi>Vulcan</hi> his altar, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Homerus &amp; Plut.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But ſithence you will needes be mad with a witnes, &amp; proue a foole in print, &amp; ſlauer out your follies in view of the world, vnder reformation, it ſtandeth not with Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> policie, or charitie, to let you ſlip vncontroled, but as <hi>Salomon</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heth to <hi>Anſwer a foole according to his follie, leaſt he braue it out, &amp; triumph in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 26. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>his owne eyes.</hi> For though a guiltles conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, like a marble ſtone, ſaith <hi>Ierome,</hi> ſhiuereth al reproches, like arrowes, ſhot againſt it:<note place="margin">Hierony. Auguſt.</note> yet as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> hath well obſerued, it is <hi>magnae crudelitatis,</hi> for a publike magiſtrate, <hi>ſic in conſciencia acquieſcere, vt famam negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat,</hi> ſo to relie vpon the innocence of his actions, that he neglect all annoyance of his good name. And therefore, <hi>Mr. Broughton,</hi> arme your ſelfe with patience, if it bee poſſible for a proud man to haue ſuch a vertue, that ſince againſt the law you haue not<note place="margin">Exod. 22. 28.</note> ceaſed <hi>to curſe the ruler of the people,</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>to reuile God his high Prieſt,</hi> which <hi>S. Paul</hi> repented hee had ignorantly done, though that Prieſt were an vſurper: and againſt the profeſſion of a <hi>Diuine,</hi> with ſuch ribauld termes, vnſauourie, and ſhameleſſe lies, yea, and contrarie to all humanitie, againſt him, who in the <hi>Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> (by your owne confeſſion) was a chiefe meanes of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment;<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Com. Hunt. ad Sed, Olam.</note> be (I ſay) as patient as you can, and <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 109.</note> 
                  <hi>let not indignation vexe you like a thing that is raw,</hi> that you may learne, in your own vaine, hereafter to rule your pen, and order your tongue, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16685:5"/> forbeare the preſſe, though you will neuer bee taught to know your ſelfe, to feele your weaknes, or regard your betters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 2.</head>
               <p>I Remember <hi>Theophylact,</hi> alluding to that place of <hi>Salomon</hi> where<note place="margin">Theophyl. in Luc.</note> he ſaith there is a <hi>Maried foole,</hi> nameth the wife <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ladie Selfloue,</hi> which vſually is attended by foure waiting maides; the firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>an inward ſelfe conceit;</hi> the ſecond <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a vaunting vtterance</hi> thereof; the third <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a vaine affection of publike ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe;</hi> the fourth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a loftie ouerweening,</hi> with <hi>a ſcornfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of others:</hi> the husband to this wife, ſaith the father, was the <hi>Phariſee,</hi> Luc. 18. who left her a widow after his death, till you,<note place="margin">Luc. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Mr. Broughton,</hi> were borne and came to age (our <hi>Engliſh Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee</hi>) for <hi>Nazianzens</hi> rule is true, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. Naz. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>Naſo. Meta. 2.</hi>
                  </note> not the nation, but the affection makes a <hi>Phariſee. Narciſſus</hi> in the Poet, neuer ſo madly admiring his own beautie, as you haue delighted in your ſelfe, in ſo much that, you may ſee, if you were not blinded ſottiſhly, how <hi>Theophraſt</hi> his prouerbe is verified in<note place="margin">Theoph. Plut.</note> you, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. You haue loued your ſelfe ſo well, that none other of iudgement either loues or likes you at all. Yet if looking your ſelfe often in this <hi>Selflouing</hi> glaſſe, you would do, as <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſaith, that is, hauing conſidered your naturall face,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ac. 1. 24.</note> you could goe away, and forget immediatly what your faſhion was, ſome hope there might be of your future humilitie: but to preuent that, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> attends you, putting you in minde of your great <hi>paines, your Concent of the Bible, your Sinai ſight, your Daniels weekes, your Rabinicall oracles, your Genealogicall Catechiſmes,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you are ſo houen and lifted vp, that with <hi>Simon Magus</hi> your <hi>Preuentor,</hi> (for that title fits him better for ſemblance of pride,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. ad Reg. pa. 3 &amp; literas ad D. Stoll.</note> then <hi>D. Bancroft,</hi> whom you call your <hi>Preuentor</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>London</hi>) as if you were borne at <hi>Noneſuch,</hi> you are not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to be accompted <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Act. 8. 9. a great <hi>Diuine,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Act. 8. 9. 10.</note> verſ. 10. the <hi>Cleerer of Diuinitie,</hi> the <hi>I per ſe I,</hi> and the belweather of Diuines (it is a poore flocke of ſheepe where the Ew muſt beare the bell) for ſo your masked Iew, <hi>viz.</hi> your ſelfe writes.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piſt. Abr. Rub. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c dicta.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold that is the wiſeman, whoſe praiſe is gone ouer the whole earth,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16685:5"/> euen Hugo Broughton.</hi> Which ſelfe conceit forgeth ſuch fancies in your head, that as the runnaway apprentice thought, the bels recalling him, told him he ſhould be <hi>Maior</hi> of <hi>London:</hi> ſo your humours building towers in the ayre, and Biſhoprickes in your fancie, faine a ſounding in your eares, that <hi>you heard the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop ſhould ſay you deſerued as good a place as himſelfe. That the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Varijs epiſtolis ad Archiep. &amp; Theſaur.</note> 
                  <hi>LL. ſhould giue out that you were</hi> Nulli ſecundus <hi>for knowledge. That the Queene ſhould ſay ſhe would not for all the preferments in the world you ſhould leaue the Realme. That ſuch a noble man ſhould tell you that her Maieſtie would, of her ſelfe, haue giuen you the Biſhoprick of S. Dauids. That Iewes call for you to conuert them.</hi> Meere buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zings of your owne conceited dizzie braine, (like him in <hi>Aelian</hi>
                  <note place="margin">AElianu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sto.</note> who thought all the great ſhips in the hauen were his owne) none of them euer meant or vttered by them, but onely inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſtrength of your opinion, pleaſing it ſelf with dreams of high deſert: which you know (<hi>Maſter Broughton</hi>) hath been the ouerthrow of many well quallified men, and was among the ſages of <hi>Greece</hi> accompted <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the principall impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">Bion in Laert</note> of many mens both proceedings and preferments: for many (ſaith the <hi>Stoike</hi>) might haue proued good ſchollers, if they<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> had not thought they had been ſo alreadie, and many had riſen to great places, but that, with <hi>Remus,</hi> they would attaine them<note place="margin">Liuy.</note> by leaping ouer the wall, not riſe to them by degrees and ſteps. And yet, <hi>Non vlli tacuiſſe nocet,</hi> if you had onely intertained this<note place="margin">Cato.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>ſelfe-conceit,</hi> ſmothering it within your breaſt, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance had been yours alone and inward, yet the world might haue taken you for a wiſeman (<hi>for euen a foole,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>his peace is counted wiſe):</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo bewitched you, that like an old bottle with new wine, vnleſſe you ſhould vent, you<note place="margin">Matth. 9.</note> would burſt. Whereupon, though the Wiſeman his counſell be, <hi>Let another man praiſe thee, not thine owne mouth; a ſtranger, not thine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>owne lips,</hi> you, <hi>vt ex ſtulto inſanus fieres,</hi> as if you were wiſer then <hi>Salomon, (for a foole,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is wiſer in his conceit, then ſeuen men</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 26. 16. Iob. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>that can giue a reaſon</hi>) muſt needes, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, be your owne He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald, and giue titles to your ſelfe, blazon your owne armes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord your owne deſerts, euen ſo palpably, that your foes floute you, and your friends pitie you. For thus you pronounce of your
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16685:6"/> ſelfe, in writing. <hi>The beſt learned in Europe thanke me moſt highly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epistolis ad Arch. &amp; Theſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Scotland writes for me. I haue found great thankes from Zurick, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, French, Dutch. I know my ſelfe inferiour to none for Hebrew and Greeke ſtudies. The beſt Diuines haue plowed with my Heyfer,</hi> (yet himſelfe neuer grew beyond a calfe.) <hi>All the learned through Chriſtendome, Iewes, Papiſts, Proteſtants, thinke my paines an honour to the Bible. Lingua quo vadis?</hi> What, maſter <hi>Hugh,</hi> will you hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolize aboue <hi>S. Gregorie,</hi> who is contented to marſhall the foure<note place="margin">Greg. epiſt.</note> generall Councels in equipage with the foure Euangeliſts, but your ſcriblets, forſooth, muſt countenance the Bible? For <hi>Honor is in honorante non honorato.</hi> But of all the moſt <hi>Thraſonicall Brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadoccion</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> 
                  <hi>ſelf-boasting,</hi> is that cogd epiſtle of <hi>Abr. Ruben<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aliâs</hi> of <hi>Hugh ap Broughton</hi> to himſelfe, (which when Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> had read, told a countrie man of ours being preſent with him, that ſure you were a very vaine man) <hi>ſcil. All thy valuation, M. Hugh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An epiſtle coyned by Br. with a Iewes ſtampe.</note> 
                  <hi>is according to the ſickle of the Sanctuarie, 20. Gerahs to a ſickle. The delights of thy moſt high perfections are in that mans throate. The ſweet ſmell of the myrrhe of thy learning (which is as ſignes and wonders in heauen and earth) is gone ouer the Ocean ſea. God hath created thee, M. Hugh, to make the honour of England more honourable. Thou art a glorie and renowne euen to the Queene her ſelfe.</hi> Beſide many other phraſes giuen in Scripture to God himſelfe, prophanely abuſed to your commendation, ſauouring not onely of arrogancie, but blaſphemie. To ſuch an outrecuidance hath your ſelfe-conceit caried you. Which gloſing letter, ſuppoſe it were true, that a Iew had written, a wiſeman would haue either anſwered at the reading thereof, as that Philoſopher did once in the like, <hi>Me hic</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diog. Laert.</note> 
                  <hi>aut ludit, aut odit.</hi> This man would procure me either ſcorne, or hatred. For hyperbolicall commendations are motiues to both.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lat. Demet.</note> Or elſe haue concealed them, leaſt the world ſhould thinke he delighted in his owne praiſes, <hi>the ſpeciall cogniſance of a foole,</hi> in <hi>Cato</hi> his wiſedome. But to take copies thereof, and diſperſe them<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ato.</note> abroad in <hi>Baſil,</hi> and ſend them into <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Geneua,</hi> that men might point at thee <hi>Leuiculum nostrum Demoſthenem,</hi> (ſo<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul. Tuſ. quaeſt.</note> you call your ſelfe in your epiſtle to the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Oxford</hi>) and ſuppoſe you to be the <hi>Homer</hi> of our time, the 7. Cities neuer<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul. Gel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul. pro Arch.</note> ſo ſtriuing for him, as nations and kingdomes challenge you,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16685:6"/> this is an extreame vanitie: marry to coyne an epiſtle of your ſelfe to your ſelfe, vnder a Iewes name, with ſuch <hi>Taratantara</hi> fictions and applauſes, not learning onely, but euen common reaſon would deeme to be a deſperate phrenſie: for as he is mad for hunger (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) which will eate his owne fleſh, ſo is he<note place="margin">Plutarch. de ſe laud.</note> much more hunger-ſtarued for commendations, who is driuen to praiſe himſelfe, eſpecially with forgeries and impoſtures. Yet, this is the <hi>Syrenicall</hi> allurement of your attendant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, who perſwades you that <hi>written letters</hi> are perſonall and priuate, and ſelfe-praiſes vnder ſeale are eaſily concealed, and therfore leaſt either enuie, or time, or ſilence ſhould ſuppreſſe them, to the preſſe with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 3.</head>
               <p>ANd hence commeth your <hi>Printed Pamphlets.</hi> Belike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it were a ſinne to ſpoyle cleane paper with baſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, you will blot i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with your fooleries, that ſo it might be ſent from the Printers preſſe to the Apothecaries ſhop, there<note place="margin">Horace epiſt.</note> to make caſes for ſpices at the beſt, <hi>Et piper &amp; quicquid chartis amicitur ineptis.</hi> Which prating rhapſodies, like <hi>Sappho</hi> his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, crying nothing but <hi>Magnus Deus Broughton,</hi> to winne you<note place="margin">Herodot.</note> the more renowme, you doe not onely dedicate to Noble men of high place, (an inſolent indiſcretion to make thoſe perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges patrones of ſuch boggard ſtuffe) but many of them moſt preſumptuouſly you front with the ſacred name of her royall Maieſtie, (as if your inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions were all <hi>Treaſure trouue, fiske royal, mines vnheard of,</hi> for Princes onely, being in deede to him that digs in them, as vnto <hi>Pompey</hi> his ſouldiers, a loſt labour, and<note place="margin">Plut. Pomp.</note> time ridiculouſly ſpent, and the ſtuffe it ſelfe according to the prouerbe <hi>Theſaurus carbones</hi>) whoſe ſingular affabilitie and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie<note place="margin">Eraſ. adag.</note> though it bee ſuch, that ſhe will vouchſafe the ſpeech of the meaneſt, and a ſmall gift from the pooreſt: yet as <hi>Augustus</hi> the Emperour, famous in <hi>Rome</hi> that way, as not diſdaining courſe intertainment where hee was inuited, when one as ſimply, as boldly, had requeſted him to his houſe, cheering him vp with<note place="margin">Macrob. Sat.</note> nothing but browne bread and leekes, at his departure gaue his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16685:7"/> hoſt this farewell, <hi>Non put âram <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e tibi tam f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>miliarem eſſe.</hi> The like anſwere may you iuſtly expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, or a ſharper rather, <hi>Master Hugh,</hi> for your fooliſh paines; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>lable to that, becauſe you are a <hi>Graecian,</hi> as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue to ſuch a cenodoxicall<note place="margin">Rhodig.</note> companion as your ſelfe, who hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cribled a pamphlet in the praiſe of Labour, with an epiſtle prefixed to King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> his booke bearing title <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the King puts out the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. and now, ſaith he, the author hath praiſed himſelfe. Were there in you that learning which you pretend, <hi>Seneca</hi> might haue taught you what puniſhment it deſerued, <hi>Principis imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eneca.</note> 
                  <hi>obſcaenis inferre,</hi> to ſet the Princes ſtampe vpon baſe veſſels, much more to dare dedicate to her ſacred Maieſtie infamous Libels, make the beſt of them, frothie conceits, fomed out from an hot mouth, working and fretting it ſelfe vpon the bit of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment. What man of common ſenſe or reaſon, would preſume to print an epiſtle to a Prince of her diuine parts, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable learning, ſingular iudgement, and menaging ſuch weightie affaires, containing nothing elſe, but a fabulous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of a Iewes letter ſent to. <hi>N.</hi> that is to the <hi>Noddy</hi> your ſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pr. Baſil. 98.</note> and appoint her who ſhould anſwer it? And, in another, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her that while you were expecting her anſwer touching your preferment, there fell ſuch foule weather vpon the land,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pr. 99.</note> that ſome <hi>godly diſpoſed ſelected you to auert Gods wrath by prayer and preaching;</hi> which you did, forſooth, by expounding <hi>Act.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>pag. 3.</hi>
                  </note> how <hi>Rempham</hi> and <hi>Chiun, Babylon and Damaſcus</hi> might be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled from <hi>Amos</hi> to <hi>Stephen,</hi> and vpon this (ſo fit a theame for foule weather) the people thanked you for cleering the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens by your paines, and Strangers thanked her Maieſtie for<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>pag. 4.</hi>
                  </note> cleering <hi>S. Stephen</hi> by your pen. Firſt proue this, what Strangers euer thanked her for you, name them, ſhew their writings, note the time, ſet downe the words, elſe are you too impudent to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe your Princes name, and the readers patience with ſuch groſſe vanities; remember what the Poet ſaid of one, almoſt as vainly proud in the opinion of his beautie, as you are of your<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>autu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gior.</note> diuinitie, <hi>Ait ſeſe vltr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> omnes nationes ſectarier, Is eſt deriſui qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quâ incedit omnibus.</hi> And as for the other, for ſhame, <hi>Brough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> (now I cannot forbeare thee) leaue to arrogate that to thy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16685:7"/> ſelfe, which all diuinitie, and God himſelfe denies thee. Thy prayers and preaching to worke miracles with God? <hi>God hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 9. Iam. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>not ſinners.</hi> The prayer of a righteous man preuailes with God: righteous he cannot bee, in the meaneſt degree, which hath neither humilitie, nor charitie. Thy prayers to ſtop the bottles of the clowdes, as <hi>Iob</hi> calleth them? the prayers of a <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 38. Pſal. 131. &amp; 127. Eſay. 47. <hi>Herod.</hi> Pſal. 109. Eſay. 66.</note> 
                  <hi>childe</hi> are as the arrowes of a Giant forcible to pearce the heauens: but proceeding from the ſpirit of <hi>Babel, I am, and there is none but I,</hi> they are like <hi>Xerxes</hi> arrowes ſhot vp againſt the Sunne, theſe reculing to their hurt that ſhot them, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to their curſe that made them. To him, ſaith God, will I incline mine eare, that hath an humbled ſpirit, and a contrite heart: which ſacrifice you could neuer yet offer, nor can, till you abaſe your hornes, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh, and diſgarboyle your ſelfe<note place="margin">Iob.</note> of thoſe corrupt affections, and loftie thoughts, which makes your perſon, whereſoeuer you come, burdenſome, and your <hi>ſurquedry</hi> intolerable. <hi>Se ipſum immolet qui Deum vult laudare,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) &amp; totum te conſumat ignis eius.</hi> And when you<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Augustinus.</hi> Pſal. 51.</note> haue made <hi>Dauids</hi> ſacrifice of your houen imaginations, and <hi>Pauls</hi> metamorphoſis of your malicious minde, then may you<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> perſwade vs that you haue wrought a miracle. But what doe I ſpeake of reaſon, or religion to a mad man? For were you not ſo, more guiltie you are of treaſon then reaſon: for in another of your <hi>Paperworkes,</hi> you preſcribe her Maieſtie a time to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre you, and if ſhe will not, <hi>you threaten that then you will forſake</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Reg.</note> 
                  <hi>the land, and of that you had ſent word to the King of Scots.</hi> A good ſubiect verily, and a great loſſe no doubt. And what ſpirit doth<note place="margin">Impr. 99.</note> that ſpeech ſauour of in your laſt epiſtle to her Maieſtie, that a chiefe Commiſſioner in her Highnes name and authoritie, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing a booke of your ſchiſmaticall fancies, you ſhould dare to ſay, <hi>that he vſed more authoritie then her Maiestie had to lend him.</hi> A good world it is, when ſuch giddie brained dottards, as you are, will limit Princes prerogatiues, and charge the <hi>High commiſſion</hi> of <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> for calling you to account for your <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious doctrine.</hi> It might goe hard with you, but that the Ciuill law pleades for your necke, in ſaying, that <hi>Furioſus &amp; impubes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. de iniur. &amp; fam. lib.</note> 
                  <hi>iniuriam facere non poſſunt quia non habent iudicium.</hi> The fooliſh
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16685:8"/> painter in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that had painted a Cocke like a Gooſe, was<note place="margin">Plut. &amp; Aelia.</note> faine to write ouer the head, <hi>this is a Cocke:</hi> you might haue ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that labour in putting your name to the epiſtles, for it is a thouſand to one, if her Maieſtie did euer loſe time to reade them, ſhe eaſily geſſed that the author went a crowing with a combe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 4.</head>
               <p>OF the like <hi>Lunaticall</hi> humour are your epiſtles to the Lords, eſpeciallie that which came from you about <hi>Midſomer</hi> moone laſt, <hi>To and againſt the Archhiſhop of Canterburie,</hi> about <hi>Sheol</hi> and <hi>Hades,</hi> ſenſeles for the period, vnſound for the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, immodeſt in reproches, vntrue for the ſlaunders, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in falſe witneſſes, ridiculous for the vanities. Wherein your laſt attendant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth play her part, with a cup of ouerwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning liquour, hauing ſo intoxicated your weake braine, (<hi>For the proudman is as he that tranſgreſſeth with wine</hi>) that as <hi>Zebul</hi> being<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bac. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d 9.</note> well tipled, tooke an whole armie of men to be but ſhadowes of mountaines, ſo you there ſcorne all others comparatiuely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all reſpect, impudently without all ſhame, vnſauourly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all diſcretion, vnſoundly without all iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, madly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all reaſon, prophanely without all religion, forgetting that thundring ſpeech of the ſpirit, as the <hi>Sept.</hi> reade it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hilo.</note> And yet this is that <hi>Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you are ſo enamoured, of which you haue ſo often boaſted, and with which you haue ſo long threatned to diſgrace his <hi>Grace;</hi> in your epiſtle to her Maieſtie, <hi>you will call him to account for all at once:</hi> in an epiſtle to the Lord Treaſurer, <hi>you will put his Graces fame in print:</hi> in your letters to <hi>D. Stoll. you will ſet his Graces fame paſt cure:</hi> in priuate letters to himſelfe, belching out vnſauourie menaces of that, which here you haue diſgorged. Wherein you haue ſpent all the <hi>vires</hi> and power you haue for the defence of a vaine paradox, and ſpit out all the <hi>virus</hi> and poyſon you could conceiue, in the abuſe of his reuerend perſon, in both fulfilled the prophecie of <hi>Eſay:</hi> In the former, hauing ſpun the ſpiders web, for your opinion heatheniſh and ridiculous; in the latter,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay. 59. 5.</note>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16685:8"/> hatching the Cockatrice egges, your phraſes and ſtile being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull and malicious: and becauſe you will be the <hi>Homeriſt</hi> of our time (although Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> his iudgement was, to a great mans ſonne, who was with him at the receipt of your Greeke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, that <hi>you might very well haue written in Latin</hi>) your anſwere ſhall bee <hi>Homer</hi>-like, to the laſt firſt. Taking this by the way, which <hi>Pindarus</hi> foretold, and you haue fulfilled, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Pind. Olymp.</note> that importunate ſelfe-boaſting brings a man to madnes: and therefore ſome not vnfitly haue deriued <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And now I anſwer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IVlian</hi> the <hi>Apostata,</hi> as good a ſcholler as your ſelfe, writing a<note place="margin">Lactant.</note> tractate againſt the Chriſtians, yet, more wiſely then honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to allure the reader, which otherwiſe would haue abhorred the booke, intituled it <hi>Ad Christianos:</hi> but you, adding gall to<note place="margin">Deut. 29.</note> wormewood, and impudencie to your ſlaunders, haue fronted your Libell with this inſcription, <hi>To and againſt the Archbiſhop of Canterburie.</hi> Wherein though you haue watched a double ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>antage, both of this time and generation, hauing curious eares, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hirſting more after great mens diſgraces, then <hi>Athens</hi> after<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> newes; and alſo of apologie, becauſe as <hi>Apuleius</hi> (he that wrote the metamorphoſis of your golden brother) hath wiſely ſaid, that <hi>Inſimulari quiuis innocens à quouis nebulone poteſt:</hi> It is an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie<note place="margin">Apul. ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> matter for euery rake ſhame to reuile an innocent, but it is neither ſafe nor fit for euery man to cleere the accuſed; not fit, becauſe if the anſwerer depend vpon him whom he defends, he ſhall be counted a flatterer: not ſafe, becauſe in the accompt of <hi>Xenophon</hi> and <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: to great men that are<note place="margin">Xenoph. Dem. de coror</note> truly vertuous, there is nothing more burdenſome, then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing of their praiſes. Yet in deſpight of enuie, <hi>ex tuo ore te iudicabis ſerue nequam.</hi> Thine owne conſcience, and the triall of<note place="margin">Luc. 19.</note> thy countenance ſhall teſtifie againſt thee, as the Prophet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.<note place="margin">Eſay. 3. 9. Exod. 22.</note> In <hi>Moſes</hi> law he that had ſlaine a Burgleyer by night had been guiltles, but if the Sunne were vp when he ſmote him he was puniſhed as a murtherer. Had you not knowne him whom
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16685:9"/> you thus haue ſmitten with your tongue, but, like <hi>Aiax</hi> in the <hi>Tragady,</hi> whipt a ram for a man, and lent your blowes at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phocles.</note> the Ciuill law might once more haue pleaded for you, <hi>Error in perſona cui fit iniuria, facit vt non oriatur actio iniuriarum.</hi> And<note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de iniur. &amp; fam. lib.</note> your excuſe might haue been either raſh indiſcretion, or falſe information: but your conſcience grounded vpon long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and certaine knowledge of the <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> great indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, from his youth, not pregnancie alone; his manifold know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, not paines onely; his ſound iudgement, not knowledge onely; his effectuall preaching, not iudgement onely; his irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible life, not preaching onely; his wiſe gouernment, not vertues onely; makes it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Philo</hi> ſpeaketh, and<note place="margin">Philo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> doubleth thy ſinne againſt thine owne head, and findes thee guiltie not onely of malicious ſlaunder to reuile the innocent, but of impudent and infamous libelling to diſhonour the name and place of ſuch a worthie and <hi>reuerend Father:</hi> of whom (if euer of any man) it may be ſaid as of <hi>Zachary,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, let not<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urip. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. 31.</note> malice be iudge, he hath walked irreproueably before God and men: and may pleade for himſelfe againſt ſuch as thou art, as <hi>Iob</hi> againſt his exulcerating comforters, <hi>Though mine aduerſarie ſhould write a booke againſt mee, would I not take it vp, and binde it as a crowne vnto me?</hi> Hauing ſo often verified that in himſelfe which Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Qui volens detrahit famae meae, nolens</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uguſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rip. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lly.</note> 
                  <hi>addit mercedi meae.</hi> For as <hi>Telephus</hi> wound <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, was healed by the ſpeare that hurt him; and the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending death to <hi>Iaſon</hi> and <hi>Prometheus,</hi> cured both: ſo, certaine it is, that neuer any durſt touch him with any crime, either for gouernment or otherwiſe, but either with an after repentance in themſelues they were confounded, or by his eminent integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in all good mens opinion they were confuted, their ſlanders working his glorie, and their owne ſhame. And yet this ſacred Prelate, this honorable Counſellor, this graue Diuine, to giue him no more titles, then that which S. <hi>Baſil</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, this<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aut. Men. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mer.</note> 
                  <hi>Seruant of God; tu tu</hi> (as one of your owles ſpeaketh in <hi>Plautus</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> he may ſay, haſt preſumed to profeſſe to write <hi>againſt.</hi> Were it as <hi>Dem.</hi> ſaid to <hi>Aeſchi:</hi> that <hi>Aeacus</hi> or <hi>Rhada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manthus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſome perſon of note, of incomparable learning, of high
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16685:9"/> place, of irreprehenſible deportment (the <hi>Reuerend Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop</hi> hauing, we will ſuppoſe it, giuen offence) ſhould haue confuted him, it had been too much for any ſuch, without due reuerence, to haue aduaunced a Rebutter <hi>againſt</hi> his <hi>Grace:</hi> for the fathers, we know, howſoeuer their higher Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates ſometimes offended the Church with infecting opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, neuer profeſt to write <hi>againſt</hi> them, but ſtill ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed their epiſtles and bookes To ſuch and ſuch. Yet this<note place="margin">Vide Bern. &amp; Aug. &amp; Hilari</note> had been tolerable in any ſuch perſon: but for a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a fantaſticall genealogiſt, a paradoxicall expoſitor, a tragicall ape, a forlorne Phariſee, a running-headed fugitiue to bee thus publikely malepart, in preſuming to write <hi>againſt</hi> an <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> auering a trueth <hi>Apostolicall,</hi> as the impudence is intolerable, ſo I wonder how ſo many, that haue fared ſo well by his <hi>Graces</hi> preferment, can with patience indure, or with ſilence brooke this inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſhameleſſe preſumption; but that it is knowne to proceede from an <hi>Archilochus</hi> leane and hidebound with hart-fretting enuie, but, as the Poet deſcribes him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Pindaru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> fatting himſelfe vp with contumelious ſcornes, and reproches. Not ſparing the holy fathers of the Church, the reuerend Beaupeeres of diuine knowledge, but giuing<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Melchiſ. p.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſome the bable, as S. <hi>Austen</hi> by name, <note n="*" place="margin">p. 49. lib. Sheol.</note> befooling the penner of the <hi>Creede</hi> not expounded to his fancie, and in a ſhort ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract calling all the Latin fathers the <hi>plague of Diuinitie.</hi> But<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad reg.</note> who can looke for more reuerence at his hand toward the Eccleſiaſticall fathers, whoſe pride hath ſo caried him paſt all grace, that he ſticketh not to traduce, euen in publike letters, his owne <hi>naturall father?</hi> ſo farre hauing been buſied in <hi>Sems progenie,</hi> that he is fallen into <hi>Chams</hi> opprobrie, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing<note place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> his father, in more vile termes then I will expreſſe, for <hi>an Aleknight and common drunkard;</hi> for <hi>an whoremaster and a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In ep. ad Arch. Eraſ. chil.</note> 
                  <hi>minion maintainer, (Turdus ſibi malum) for a raunger and a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; euen in the very ſame letters, wherein it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the foule-mouthed varlet to intitle the moſt <hi>Reuerend Archbiſhop</hi> (I tremble to write it) <hi>Nebulo,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp; ruina regni.</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16685:10"/> What ſaith Saint <hi>Iude? Yet Michael the Archangell, encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iude ver. 9. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the deuill, durſt not blaspheme.</hi> But ſuch a tongue-murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Cain,</hi> an ambitious <hi>Balaamite,</hi> (ſtill bawling for prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) cannot withhold, but laboureth like a flie about the candle, to periſh in the gainſaying of <hi>Corah.</hi> And therefore writing about the <hi>deſcent into Hell,</hi> hath inflamed his owne tongue with the fire of hell, that as by his genealogicall gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he hath abuſed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo by his gehennical curſings<note place="margin">Iac. 3.</note> he might ſet on fire <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and kindle a diſſention about the deſcention, wherein there hath been ſo long conſent. <hi>Hominem malignum forſan te credant alij, Ego eſſe miſerum credo</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Martial.</note> 
                  <hi>cui placet nemo.</hi> Other perchance will geſſe thee to bee a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant ſlaunderer, but I rather take thee to bee a wretched skrat pinde with enuie, whom none can pleaſe, either fathers in Diuinitie, or fathers by authoritie, or parents naturall; but as the <hi>Argyraspides</hi> anſwered ſome forward youths, whoſe<note place="margin">Plut.</note> ſteps thou paſeſt, ſo ſay I, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 6.</head>
               <p>NOw if any man would know what miniſtred the fuell to this flagrant controuerſie about hell, to this publike challenge and open confutation; nothing that the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop</hi> hath either publikely preached, or at any time printed in that cauſe. But the briefe, and the trueth is this; <hi>Doctor Andrewes</hi> hauing, in a Sermon vpon that article, ſtrongly out of Scripture and Fathers confirmed the deſcent, according to the words, you, forſooth, not worthie to bee ballanced with him for ſound learning, (howſoeuer moſt impudently you tell the old <hi>L. Treaſurer</hi> that he ſaid, knowing you to bee his<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Theſ.</note> better in ſtudies, that he would yeeld to you) you I ſay, <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus, quantulus?</hi> preſſe into the pulpit not long after to refute his doctrine: which had it been in charitie and zeale for the trueth, it had been more ſchollerlike and diuine: but, as your manner is, with ſuch contempt and contumelies to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16685:10"/> of the man, you held that courſe, which neither policie for example, nor religion for peace could tolerate, vpon which you were called before his <hi>Grace,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Here<note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>yd.</note> you began to ſtirre, not onely contemptuouſly refuſing to come, but malepartly anſwering his <hi>Grace</hi> with ſcornfull let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſubſcribing them, very familiarly at the beſt, in truth moſt ſaucely, <hi>Tuus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, your fellow ſouldier. (<hi>Sir Hugh</hi> your fellowes are in <hi>Bedlem.</hi>) And as that <hi>Souldier,</hi> your <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne</hi> and predeceſſor in the Comedie, ſaid of himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note place="margin">Miles gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> he had deigned his preſence to one that requeſted it. <hi>Non, aedepol, tu ſcis, mulier, quantum ego honorem nunc illi habeo:</hi> ſo you ſtand vpon it mightily, in a large volume, that you <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ad Dominu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Theſaur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> his <hi>Grace</hi> very much, in calling your ſelfe his <hi>Souldier fellow,</hi> yea they are your owne words, that you <hi>vouchſafed</hi> to call him a fellow in iudgement with you for religion. Nay further you truſt, you ſay, that <hi>her Maiestie reioyceth</hi> to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with your defence for religion. Baſe vaſſall, who will not be taught the dutie of a ſubiect to a Prince, but will meaſure her learning by thy modell. Her Highnes knowes better then thy ſelfe, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Herodian,</hi> and other Grecians, as alſo <hi>Commilitones</hi> among the Romanes, is giuen by an <hi>Euphemiſmus</hi> of Captaines to their ſouldiers, to knit<note place="margin">Herod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Thucy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> their hearts to them by ſuch familiar titles: and in the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being but twiſe vſed, it is vouchſafed by <hi>Paul,</hi> the great<note place="margin">Philip. 2. Philem. ver. 3.</note> Apoſtle, vnto his inferiours, but neuer reciprocall. When you were fellow of <hi>Christs Colledge</hi> (whereof came the prouerbe) that there were in the houſe twelue fellowes and a foole, which was <hi>your ſelfe,</hi> you being allowed the ſame <hi>diet</hi> with the <hi>Maſter,</hi> if you had written to him, would you haue called him your fellow commoner? Had you written to <hi>Iohn Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie, and called him your <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and fellow Miniſter, degrees being equall, it had ſauoured of ſome wiſedome and learning: but inditing your letters to <hi>the moſt reuerend Archbiſhop,</hi> and ſubſcribing them with that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepart ſtile <hi>tuus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is ſurely a <hi>ſolaeciſme</hi> in manners, and argueth great want of diſcretion, yea of learning: for <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16685:11"/> will tell you, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and<note place="margin">Xenoph.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are all one, that is a fellow ſouldier and a follower, and ſo in authors ſynonymically confounded, and euer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied from the better to the meaner, but not vpward: and ſoothly ſo you meant, for in the very ſame epiſtle, you ſay,<note place="margin">Ad Dom. Theſ.</note> that you know your ſelfe to bee his <hi>Graces</hi> better, and ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in ſtudie, and knowledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 7.</head>
               <p>AFter this from letters, running out of the land, (as you pretend) you ſet vpon him with this late <hi>Libell,</hi> wherein is contained (as you tell her Maieſtie) <hi>the marrow of your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Reg.</note> Which ſpeech of yours puts me in minde of ſome Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers opinions in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who write that the marrow<note place="margin">Plut. Agis. Ouid Metam.</note> of dead mens bodies, eſpecially the back-bone, as <hi>Ouid</hi> will, doth oft turne into ſnakes. Such marrow, verely ſerpentine and viperous, doth your booke affoord, poyſonfully ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his <hi>Grace</hi> with more ſpight then hurt; for when you haue varied your reproches with ſuch voluntarie phraſes, as your addle head and malicious ſtomacke could gather <hi>è triuio,</hi> the concluſion is, that he is <hi>vtterly vnlearned.</hi> There were ſome Philoſophers ſo mad to ſay, that the Snow was blacke; and<note place="margin">Anax. Ariſt. de doelo.</note> ſome Mathematicians ſo ſenſeles, as to auouch that the earth went round; and ſome Rhetoricians ſo impudent, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> for barbarous and harſh; and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus,</hi> as vaine an Hiſtorian, almoſt, as you are a Diuine, being<note place="margin">Plut. Nicias.</note> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a writer of yeſterda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es broode, vilified and abaſed the credit of that worthie and famous <hi>Thucydides,</hi> the mirrour of Hiſtorians. Thine owne conſcience, <hi>Brough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> tels thee, that the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> his indefatigable paines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed his learning; his learning ſetled his iudgement, his iudgement brought on his grauitie, each of theſe in ſeuerall wonne him credit and degrees, and all together adorned him with preferment. Much is the Vniuerſitie beholding to you, and men of good iudgement you make the learned
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16685:11"/> heads of that time, who ſelected him aboue the reſt, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to bee the Lady <hi>Margarets</hi> Reader, and after that, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted him to bee the <hi>Chiefe profeſſor</hi> in Diuinitie, were he ſo <hi>vnlearned,</hi> as your <hi>Loftines</hi> makes him. And it is to bee ſuppoſed by any ſenſible man, that her Maieſtie aduauncing him to this higheſt dignitie, and, after that, calling him into her Priuie Councell, tooke him to bee a man both of ſound iudgement, and at the leaſt, of ſome learning. But this is the effect and affection of men, ſo farre houen with <hi>ſurquedrie</hi> and ſelfe-loue, as <hi>Menippus</hi> in the Moone tooke men for<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Iac. 18.</note> moates, ſo <hi>Phariſaïcally</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to annihilate all others; and as <hi>Philo</hi> hath excellently deſcribed them, as if he had anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized you, to accompt all beſides themſelues <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Philo</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (they are your owne words of his <hi>Grace</hi>) ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh, vnlearned, rifraffe, nobodie. Briefly, all Diuinitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides yours is <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and all learning to yours is rudenes. But may it pleaſe your great <hi>Masterſhip</hi> to giue a reaſon why you count and call him ſo <hi>vnlearned?</hi> His Lectures in the Schooles; his diſputations at Commencements; his Sermons popular both in Court, citie and countrie; his encounters with ſchiſmatikes in print; his aſſiduous reading in any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancie from buſines; his ſound iudgement in points of any controuerſie: all theſe haue perſwaded other to glorifie God in him, and moued the <hi>Prince</hi> to aduance him for them. Your reaſon is double. Firſt, <hi>He hath not plowed with your heyfer.</hi> You delight much in that prouerb, repeating it fiue times in your letters and pamphlets, and ſurely it accommodates your ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die well. For as that is but a barren ſoyle, and a light ground that is broken vp with a Cow, ſo are your labours trifles which are wrought out by <hi>Phantaſie.</hi> Againe, <hi>Sampſons</hi> hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer was his wife, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> skittiſh huſwife, a Philiſtine to an Iſraelite, a treacher to her husband; yours is <hi>Genealogie,</hi> a wanton ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and, as you vſe it, a ſtranger to ſound learning, a betrayer of profitable Diuinitie; his heyfer robd him of his beſt ſtrength; and yours hath bereaued you of your fiue wits; the weakning of his ſtrength loſt his libertie and his light, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16685:12"/> both theſe together brought an houſe vpon his head: your braines weaknes hath periſhed your learning, and abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you the land, and, I will not propheſie, but remember thy end and thou ſhalt doe the better. Your meaning is he hath not ſpent his yeeres in the <hi>Hebrew Rabbins.</hi> Why? you that are <hi>the great ſcholler of the world,</hi> remember you not that of <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, It is not all one kinde of<note place="margin">Pind. Olymp. 9.</note> learning that maintaines and adornes vs all? And you <hi>the ſpeciall cleerer of Diuinitie,</hi> haue you forgot the diuerſitie of gifts by the ſame ſpirit, ſome to haue tongues, ſome prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> ſome interpretation? Is Diuinitie ſo neere driuen, that as <hi>Rahel</hi> cried, <hi>Giue me children, or els I dye:</hi> ſo it muſt ſay, giue me<note place="margin">Gen. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Rabbins,</hi> or els I periſh? Who like yong men with gray haires, as the Poet ſpeaketh, carie titles of <hi>Fatherhood</hi> and <hi>Maſterſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pindarus.</note> being but <hi>Punies,</hi> either for time or skill, compared with the Fathers. For if a man ſhould aske you in <hi>Iacobs</hi> phraſe, where<note place="margin">Gen. 31.</note> were they yeſterday, or before yeſterday? your <hi>Talmudists</hi> many hundred yeeres after Chriſt, and your Philoſophers<note place="margin">Pic. Mirand. Rhod.</note> ſcarſe 300. yeeres old. And howſoeuer there be that equalize ſome of them with S. <hi>Paul</hi> his time, yet none of thoſe worthie ſtreams deriuing their diuine knowledge from the Scriptures fountaine, the great Fathers and Doctors of the Church, I meane, did euer mention any of them, to my remembrance, vnleſſe it be <hi>Hierome,</hi> of whom anone; I am ſure not borrow<note place="margin">Hier. tom. 3.</note> any direction of interpretation from them. And the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent brightnes of the <hi>Trueth,</hi> which in Chriſtendome burnes ſtill ſo gloriouſly, is borrowed from theſe mens lampes, not any way nouriſhed with <hi>Rabbins</hi> oyle. And ſo, by your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both ancient Fathers and moderne writers are as vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vnlearned as the <hi>Archbiſhop.</hi> I craue pardon of his <hi>Grace</hi> for abaſing him in paralell with ſuch an one as thou art. But he from the beginning of his ſtudies, directed the ayme of his learning to thoſe two ſcopes which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſet vp, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ver.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> 12. and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> verſ. 40. the building and ornament of Gods Church. Like <hi>Zacharies</hi> good ſhepheard carying two ſtaues<note place="margin">Zach. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Bands</hi> and <hi>Beautie.</hi> The ſource of which building he reared
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16685:12"/> vp by opening the capable myſteries of the Trinity, the work of our redemption, the incarnation of our Sauiour, the force of prayer, the effects of faith, the ſtrength of loue and vnitie, the right vſe of the Sacraments, the meanes to ſaluation, the horror of ſinne, the comforts of the ſpirit, with the power thereof in the Scripture, in the Miniſterie, in the conſcience, moſt of theſe being points in <hi>capite,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh:<note place="margin">Coloſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to which he ioyning, by Gods aſſiſtance, good example of life, and by authoritie inioyning maintenance of vnanimitie and vniformitie, informed the ignorant, and reformed the froward, and got reuerence of all. Whereas thy great ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boaſted learning is like that <hi>Theſſalian Scopas</hi> his wealth, for as he counted himſelfe, therefore, happie and rich, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note place="margin">Plut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. Mai.</note> his whole reuenewes conſiſted <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in nifles and things vnprofitable: ſo doe you thinke your ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable in knowledge, becauſe your <hi>Rabbins</hi> haue taught you who was <hi>Melchiſedecks</hi> father, and what was the age of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and what meant <hi>Abacucks meſſe of potage;</hi> which <hi>Nazianzene</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, trifling, not learning, and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Naz.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the Apoſtle moſt fitly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> knowledge ſo nicknamed:<note place="margin">1. Tit. 6.</note> Nay, they can tell you, who were before <hi>Adam,</hi> and the name of the man which was his ſchoolemaſter, and will ſhew you that the Sunne in the firmament hath been eternall, that the<note place="margin">Vide Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in Mich. &amp; Ram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utarch.</note> law was giuen before the creation, that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the worlds. Neither are their workes like <hi>Homer</hi> his <hi>Aegypt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. or the <hi>Polypus head</hi> one thing good and another pernicious: but, as Maſter <hi>Beza,</hi> a man as skilfull in the <hi>Rabbins</hi> as you, Sir, writeth oft, they are <hi>pleni in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eptijs</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bez. in Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; blaspemijs,</hi> full of ridiculous fables and horrible blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies; and therefore by Maſter <hi>Caluins</hi> iudgement and counſell, the reading of them to be auoyded, as writings <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cal. in Hag.</note> 
                  <hi>nulla adhibenda fides.</hi> And graunt there be, as the Earle of<note place="margin">Pic. in Hept.</note> 
                  <hi>Mirand.</hi> writeth, the myſteries of the profoundeſt Diuinitie in ſome of their <hi>Cabaliſts,</hi> yet, as the Poet ſaid, <hi>Turpe eſt diffic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les habere nugas, &amp; ſtultus labor eſt ineptiarum;</hi> and the ſame may<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ial.</note> with more eaſe, and ſafetie, and with leſſe loſſe of good time
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16685:13"/> be found in the Fathers and claſſicall authors Chriſtian: for S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> another manner of Hebrician then <hi>Braggadoccion Broughton,</hi> confeſſeth that their <hi>aniles fabul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> are ſo infinite,<note place="margin">Hier. tom 3.</note> and their volumes ſo many, that it would aske long time euen to runne ouer them, beſides the traditions ſo filthie, <hi>vt erubeſcam dicere,</hi> ſaith the father, that a Chriſtian would bluſh to reade them, and lothe to heare them. And yet with this Rabbinicall rubbiſh and vntempered mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter haue you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured a lomie and ſandie building many yeeres, telling the poore ignorant artizans in <hi>London</hi> of <hi>Caina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in <hi>Luke,</hi> of <hi>Chiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in <hi>Amos,</hi> of 430. yeeres in the <hi>Iudges,</hi> of an excellent Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme to be framed out of the 1. of <hi>Matth.</hi> and the 3. of <hi>Luke.</hi> And which was a mightie timber log to reare, to perſwade them that <hi>Adam</hi> fell the firſt day of creation, or elſe the Lion muſt eate graſſe (did not the Echo of the Church leaue out the g. r. and giue you the reſt?) and for this you accompt your ſelfe the <hi>Non parel</hi> for knowledge, and worthie of an <hi>Earle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Com. Hunting.</note> if learning had the guerdon. Neither was it needfull to fill your boaſting bookes with glorying of your reading <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binisticall;</hi> for as they which ſuck the milke of ill nurſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarch.</hi> Gen. 30.</note> proue ill conditioned: and as <hi>Iacob<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſheepe, in ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming time, by the ſight of pilled rods brought forth party co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured lambes; ſo your <hi>ſelfe-conceiuing phan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſie,</hi> being euer in the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aning mood,</hi> by your continuall reading thoſe fabulous maſters, bringeth into light nothing but fantaſticall and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie coloured pild conceits halfe mad, halfe fooliſh; and by ſucking of their traditions, as of their milke, you haue taken in their conditions. For this is generally obſerued in thoſe Iewiſh writers, that <hi>Volunt haberi pro oraculo quicquid illis in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cal. in Hoſ.</note> 
                  <hi>mentem venit.</hi> And is not this your vaine? Whatſoeuer you obtrude vpon vs in your Paperworkes, without ground or reaſon, they, which will not yeeld and ſubſcribe, bee they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo learned, are but <hi>Hogs</hi> to pearles; diſgracers of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and be they neuer ſo religious, enemies they are to God his trueth, <hi>Iulians, Lucians, Apostates, Scoffers, vnſetled in their</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Oxon. Acad.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtudies.</hi> But in ſooth, <hi>Sir Hugh,</hi> had nature through cuſtome,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16685:13"/> or bitternes from diſcontentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, forced you into this <hi>Rabſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 38.</note> vaine againſt the <hi>reuerend Archbiſhop,</hi> yet ſomething you ſhould haue obiected which had bin probable: but ſo blunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, like another <hi>Ned,</hi> to call him whom her Royall Maieſtie, the Nobleſt perſonages, both the Vniuerſities, the whole Church, for his ſtudies, through his confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, by his labours extant, and imployments daily, acknowledge, reuere, and preferre as a moſt iudicious and graue Diuine, to call him, I ſay, <hi>vtterly vnlearned, and vnable to iudge of Diuinitie,</hi> will bee counted not impudencie onely, but a phrenſie. What ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den conſtellation hath wrought this ſtraunge <hi>Metamorphoſis,</hi> that <hi>Tam ſubito coruus, qui modo cygnus erat,</hi> that he, whom you<note place="margin">Martia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> not long ſince made vmpire of that great controuerſie twixt <hi>D. R.</hi> and your ſelfe, whoſe arbitrement (which you ſay made for you) you triumph in, and <hi>accompt of as great validitie as the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iſt. ad Oxo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fine.</note> 
                  <hi>Princes owne;</hi> yea when you thought the meaneſt of him, it pleaſed you to vouchſafe him the name of a <hi>Scholler of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epist. ad Nob. Ang.</note> 
                  <hi>good accompt in ſpeech for a Baron,</hi> that now vpon the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, within a yeeres compaſſe at moſt, he, I ſay, ſhould proue vtterly vnlearned, and vnable to iudge of learning? But true is that of <hi>Salomon, Non recipit ſtultus verba prudentiae, niſi ea</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>dixeris quae verſantur in corde eius.</hi> And as <hi>Augustine</hi> writeth of ſome male contents, like the Iſraelites, <hi>Niſi homini Deus pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 32. <hi>Augustinus.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Deus non erit;</hi> with them God ſhall bee no God, if hee fulfill not their luſts; nor with you any man ſhall be learned longer then he ſubſcribes to your fancies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 8.</head>
               <p>BVt what art thou that iudgeſt thy betters? Remember him that ſaid, <hi>Hypocrita eijce primûm trabem.</hi> The deepeſt<note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> point of learning, and moſt profitable which euer thou wert conuerſant in, was <hi>Gabriels</hi> meſſage and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niels</hi> weekes: wherein, as many heretofore, ſo of late Maſter <hi>Liuely</hi> hath with ſound learning controled your wiſedomnes, and till you haue anſwered him, (which you more ſcornefully threaten,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16685:14"/> then you dare, or can learnedly performe) neuer brag of your knowledge, nor bumbaſt your bookes with ſuch <hi>Thraſonicall</hi> threates, <hi>Nihili coaxatio.</hi> I can tell you, you haue rouſed a lion.<note place="margin">Plautu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Virgil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Neſcis quantus in clypeum inſurgat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quo turbin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> torqueat hastam.</hi> As for your other learning, except your tongues, (wherein you are no extraordinarie man in Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> his opinion) it is all contained within one word <hi>Geneal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gie.</hi> For like the painter in the Poet, who could expreſſe in colours nothing well, <hi>ſed ſimulare cupreſſum,</hi> if any man would haue his pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratius.</note> taken, or any other picture pourtraied, his anſwere ſtill was, will it pleaſe you that I ſhall paint a Cypreſſe tree? Semblable is your skill: conferre we with you about ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall points of ſaluation, preſently you are vpon vs with <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedecks</hi> father, or whether <hi>Kis</hi> or <hi>Mord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> were in the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, and herein like <hi>Sard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igellius</hi> in <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ce, ab o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> you are in for all day, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> it is your<note place="margin">Hor. Sat. 3.</note> element: mary take you thence, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> noteth of ſome ſuch like your ſelfe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, you are like him who<note place="margin">Piut. Lucul.</note> while hee holds his peace is a wiſeman in <hi>Salomons</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Remember you not (<hi>you Cynoſura and Lucifer of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſtupor and admiration of the world, the admirable ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Brittiſh ſoyle</hi>) how in <hi>Leydon</hi> thruſting your ſelfe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to diſpute, the queſtion being about <hi>Originall ſinne,</hi> within two or three ſyllogiſmes you had wrong in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie of <hi>Melchiſedecks parents?</hi> and there you might ſay, as <hi>Cato</hi> when hee had got his ſword, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, now I am<note place="margin">Piut. Cat. iun.</note> where I would be. And was it not <hi>you, our Hector, and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as, the propugnacle of Engliſh faith, and the Epitome of all learning,</hi> when you had by meanes laboured in your ſelfe to be a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puter with certaine Papiſts in priſon, hauing to that purpoſe laded a porter with huge volumes, euen in the very entrance of the conflict, the controuerſie ariſing which tranſlation of the Bible ſhould determine, and you taking the <hi>Septuag.</hi> and they replying that there were diuers copies, many editions and great diuerſities of them, and therfore asking you which you would ſtand to? very learnedly, iudiciouſly, and ſoundly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16685:14"/> you anſwered, <hi>I will be iudged by that Septuag. copie which was found in a wall at Geneuah.</hi> You choked them preſently, but it was with laughter. And for your myſteries, wherein you challenge ſuch a grace aboue his <hi>Grace,</hi> for plaine, and yet<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Reg.</note> profound expoſition: firſt, as high points, as obſcure, and, I am ſure, more in number are within the compaſſe of S. <hi>Iohns Reuelation,</hi> then in <hi>Daniels</hi> prophecie, and thoſe the <hi>Reuerend Archbiſhop</hi> (of whoſe <hi>Grace</hi> ſtill I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raue pardon for this diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement offered him in comparing him with thee) vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded both learnedly and profitably, to this daies remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, in the <hi>Doctors Chayre</hi> at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> before thou wert crept out of thy <hi>Alphabeticall ſhell:</hi> and doeſt thou talke of plainnes, which makeſt riddles of eaſie hiſtories? Let him that reades iudge of perſpicuitie in this example, among<note place="margin">Ep. impr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 97. in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> many other, printed and ſent by thee to the Councell. <q>
                     <hi>Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uck brought Daniel a meſſe of potage, whereas the ſentence written in great letters, The iuſt ſhall liue by faith, this for two points. Iuſtice challenge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of Daniel to haue ſtopped the lions mouth, and faith, told by the King of him, made the ſaying of the amiable Prophet to be the meſſe of potage to him that alwaies maketh God the iudge.</hi>
                  </q> Where is your heyfer now to vnfold your riddle? It is no marueile you ſo affect the <hi>Scottiſh miſt;</hi> for where the head doth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the tongue m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt needes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: And now whether is <hi>Daniel</hi> or<note place="margin">Praefat. ad Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel.</note> you the <hi>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mentor of ſoules?</hi> Yea but ſay you, his <hi>Grace</hi> hath borrowed all his knowledge from the Fathers, (<hi>hui, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>crile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi>) but mine is wrought out of mine owne inuention. So<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Reg.</note> of all other creatures the Spider workes his webbe out of his<note place="margin">Pli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y.</note> owne ſubſtance, but the ſtrongeſt webbe a poore flye may breake. And <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt commonly come of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> But in trueth, <hi>M. Broughton,</hi> diſſemble not by whom you thriue and line: In <hi>Herodotus</hi> you may remember a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie whereof came th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prouerbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The table of the Sun,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. ex Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</note> a field wherein euery morning there were victuals ſound readie ſcattered for any th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t would gather them, which the pooreſt ſort ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly did thinke had come from heauen by the Sunnes influence, whereas indeed the Magiſtrates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16685:15"/> them thither cloſely and vnknowne to the people: and <hi>Bel</hi> his prieſts priuily lurched the viands, which were<note place="margin">Dan. 14.</note> ſuppoſed to be deuoured by the Idoll: ſo cloake your ſtealth as cloſely as you can, (like a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> ſence)<note place="margin">Demoſt. &amp; Vlp. in cundem.</note> there are ſome that can tell and ſmell from whence you bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and gleane your much bragd-of <hi>Concent,</hi> and your glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: and if you continue exaſperating, there are that will ſcatter aſhes to deſcrie your footing, and deplume your bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed feathers, returning you like a Coote, telling you that<note place="margin">Aeſop. Horat.</note> euen for thoſe two places, whereof you arrogate to your ſelfe the firſt <hi>apocalyps;</hi> that <hi>Mercerus,</hi> is your great maſter for<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Reg.</note> S. <hi>Steuens Rempham,</hi> vpon <hi>Amos:</hi> and S. <hi>Austen</hi> your <hi>Index</hi> and <hi>gnomon</hi> for S. <hi>Peters</hi> place of preaching to the ſpirits. And<note place="margin">Epiſt. contra Arch. p. 10.</note> whereas you ſay (after your ſaucie manner in a <hi>cothurnicall</hi> challenge) that if his <hi>Grace</hi> cannot ſee that you haue <hi>cleered Peter</hi> more then any before, the cauſe is his ignorance in the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> Why? ſillie fellow, his <hi>Grace</hi> will not only anſwer thee with <hi>Salomon,</hi> that <hi>there is nothing now which hath not been</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1. <hi>Auguſtinus.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſaid before:</hi> but will reach the 99. epiſtle of S. <hi>Austen,</hi> and there will ſhew thee whence thou hadſt the pureſt light for clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring S. <hi>Peter.</hi> Onely here is the difference, as the Poet ſaid, <hi>At male cum recitas incipit eſſe tuus.</hi> Whatſoeuer is ſound in<note place="margin">Martial.</note> thy writings it is borrowed: but the <hi>Lunaticall</hi> conceits, which therewith are blended, are thine owne. And this is ſufficient for your firſt great challenge of his <hi>Graces</hi> vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nednes, his ignorance of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> traditions, <hi>viz.</hi> the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probry of Chriſtianitie, and the ſcumme of Diuinitie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in leaſt you ſhould be counted as the onely malicious ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, and detractor of ſo reuerend a perſon, you call to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <hi>D. Sarauia,</hi> who told you, aſſe you ſay, that he could not beate into his <hi>Graces</hi> head the bare conceit of your deep ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.<note place="margin">Varijs epiſtolis ad Reg. Theſ. Arch.</note> Yea but <hi>D. Sar.</hi> cries out, <hi>Os impudens,</hi> and requeſted one to tell you that you did falſly belie him in this, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in this kinde you name him: and thinkes verely it is but your ſpleene againſt him, breaking out in reuenge of an old quarell: for your <hi>Masterſhip</hi> being in loue with a rich
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16685:15"/> Marchant ſtrangers daughter, and vſing the good Doctor as a mediatour for the match, the father a wiſe graue man, but once hearing of <hi>Broughtons</hi> name, in no caſe would admit his daughter the ſpeech or preſence of ſuch a giddie headed <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſard:</hi> and vpon this you raued in your paſſions againſt the Doctor, chafing extreamely that he had not ſufficiently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended you ſo highly as you deſerued. And therefore he takes this to bee but the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and vomit of a cholericke ſtomacke, to make him an author of a malicious ſlaunder.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 9.</head>
               <p>YOur ſecond reaſon is, that the <hi>Archb.</hi> is no <hi>Graecian,</hi> nor knoweth one letter of the new Teſtament. <hi>Qui ſemel ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recund ae limites tranſilijt, knauiter fit impudens.</hi> Who knowes it not (<hi>Broughton</hi>) that, in his publike Lectures, he euer read out of the Greeke Teſtament, and hath brought vp ſome vnder his priuate tuition, which are able to paſſe through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part thereof as readily for the Grammer as thy ſelfe, and more ſoundly for iudgement, (for thou art mad,) and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either thy calfe or heyfer dare challenge thee at the Greeke Teſtament, for a better Benefice then that which a <hi>London Alderman</hi> ſhould haue paide an hundred pound for, to thy behoofe, by thine aduice? And how knoweth your <hi>Rabbinſhip</hi> that he is no Grecian? <hi>For he hath falſely tranſlated</hi>
                  <note place="margin">pag. 56. 57.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and by it hath marred all Diuinitie and diſcipline.</hi> It is a mightie word, belike, that carrieth ſuch weight. But pull in your eares you <hi>Cumane</hi> beaſt for all your <hi>Lions skin:</hi> an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then potſherd though it be gilded will eaſily diſcouer it ſelfe, ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> He is very ſimple who knowes not your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">Prou. 26.</note> it is a <hi>Biſhopricke</hi> you haue expected, and hunted after mainly; and defeated of your hope, as being a very lumpe of intolerable pride, and ſingular indiſcretion, now you would faine currie fauour with the <hi>Preſbyterian faction,</hi> though the time was, when they angred you, that you could call them <hi>ignorant hotliuered fellowes, of an vnſeaſoned zeale.</hi> But to<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Oxon.</note>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16685:16"/> your reaſon. <hi>His Grace in his anſwere to the Admonition,</hi> (for<note place="margin">Reſp. ad Admo. pag. 15. ſect. 3.</note> thither you reuoke vs) <hi>expounds <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Matth. 20. a tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall and lustfull gouernment, exorbitant from the milde courſe of law and iustice, ſuch as the Heathens vſed ouer their ſubiects with oppreſſion and vnlimited licence.</hi> And very fitly and fully hath he ſo tranſlated it, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in compoſition is not idle, but ſignifies<note place="margin">Budeus. Euſtatius.</note> either as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> an addition; or as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> an oppoſition; or as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a tranſgreſſion. Againſt this you bring two arguments, both borrowed, by your leaue, from the inuention of that great replier againſt the <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> and that is ſome diſcredit for<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Nob. fine.</note> you, that diſdained to bee any Biſhops Chaplaine, to bee a <hi>Preſbyters licktrencher:</hi> for you, the graund Mintmaſter of learning in our age, <hi>ſapere ex commentarijs,</hi> and to haue <hi>ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sen. Quintil.</note> 
                  <hi>atramentalem non mentalem:</hi> we expect from you, <hi>ſtrange flowre of Athens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> things new and vnheard of. Is your owne heyfer now decayed, that you muſt borrow two calues from him? and vſe the helpe of his art, when <hi>Plutarch</hi> tels you that of all artizans <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cartwrights</hi> doe make nothing<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plut.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſtraight, but as their inſtruments are bowed, ſo their work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip is crooked? <hi>Quanto tu melius hoc inueniſſes Thraſo?</hi> But<note place="margin">Terent. pag. 56.</note> the firſt is, <hi>S. Luke puts it without</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and therfore euen <hi>a ſimple and ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les gouernment is forbidden</hi> the Cleargie. I anſwere, that as the authors of this argument, being great patrones of the ſecond mariage after diuorce by the partie innocent, when they are vrged out of S. <hi>Luke.</hi> chap. 16. 18. that <hi>Whoſoeuer put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 16. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>away his wife, and marieth another, committeth adulterie,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out limitation or exception, ſend vs backe for a <hi>niſi</hi> vnto S. <hi>Matthew</hi> 19. 9. and ſo for that matter <hi>Luke</hi> muſt be iudged<note place="margin">Matth. 19. 9.</note> by <hi>Matthew.</hi> By the ſame authoritie we remit them and you from S. <hi>Luke</hi> to S. <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Marke,</hi> for the ſimple to bee<note place="margin">Matth. 20. Luc. 22.</note> expounded by the compound. Your ſecond ſtolne argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, that <hi>our Sauiour ſpeaketh of thoſe rulers which were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> beneficiall men, and therefore all, euen the mildeſt gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is meant by</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Your huge learning might haue controled either their ignorance, if they kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w it not, or their bad conſcience, and your owne to, if knowing you ſhould
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16685:16"/> write the contrarie, that titles of Heathen princes were giuen either by a flattering <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or by an ironicall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Plutarch</hi> calles them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, popular applauſes puffed with<note place="margin">Plut. Demet.</note> a breath, and drawne backe with another. As they which cried <hi>Oſanna</hi> one day to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on whom the next they cried<note place="margin">Matth. 21.</note> out <hi>Cruciſige.</hi> For thoſe princes whom ſome of their ſubiect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intituled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as patrones in their gouernment, other called them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as deuourers of their people. As the ſame <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>l. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 12. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> at one time was ſaluted both <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious prince, and a furious tyrant. And the ſame, of <hi>Caeſar, Tranquillus</hi> ſheweth in an excellent example. And if <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> a man better read in Heathen ſtories then either you or your author, had been conſulted, he would, in a moſt learned diſcourſe to this purpoſe, haue taught you that <hi>Aristides</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled all other princes, in deſeruing to bee ſaluted by the name of <hi>luſt,</hi> whereas all the reſt delighted to be called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>City-ſpoylers, thund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts, ſubduers, Egles, Hawkes,</hi> reioycing in thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>es of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, rather then in names of mildnes and vertue. And the Romane ſtories demonſtrate that the poſie of their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours was, according to their fancie and practiſe, <hi>Si libet, licet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amon. Carac.</note> If thoſe other titles were giuen them, it came from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples gloſing, not their deſert: as that title did from a Draper, who writing a booke vnder your patronage, dedicated it <hi>To the Reuerend Father Hugh Broughton:</hi> as if you had been ſome Biſhop, whereas we know you to be an ordinarie Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and no more then a Maſter in Arts, or Bachelor of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie at the moſt. A third argument you adde, and a man would ſweare it is your owne by the follie thereof; <hi>The Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 57. 1. Tim. 2.</note> muſt not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> out of 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. If by the <hi>Preſbyterie</hi> you meane their <hi>Clerolaïcall Conſistorie,</hi> let them anſwere you, and defend their authoritie, which approue and would erect that <hi>Confuſed bench:</hi> if our gouernment <hi>Epiſcopall,</hi> I then tell you, that S. <hi>Baſil</hi> calleth you <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a counterfeiting<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> coyner of Scriptures. This place you might haue kept till your mariage, for S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth husbands there to keepe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16685:17"/> their wiues from ſoueraintie, and not ſuffer them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to take head and ouerrule: and if you will needes, by your vncontroled authoritie, vnderſtand it as the Apoſtle <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">Eph. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>de ſponſis ſpiritualibus,</hi> it makes for vs in this proportion. The wife muſt not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but ſubmit her ſelfe to her husband as her head: ſo the Biſhops being husbands to their ſeuerall charges, as they muſt loue them and cheriſh them, ſo withall to keepe them vnder and in ſubiection, leaſt they ſhould <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, take head againſt their rulers and ſpirituall husbands. Yet ſtill you adde, or rather madde on, <hi>If his Grace had any Greeke, or conſcience, he would haue expounded <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> by other ſcriptures.</hi> Put on your ſpectacles you purblind and proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind <hi>Phariſee,</hi> and view his anſwere to <hi>T. C. p.</hi> 69. and ſee his interpretation confirmed by a paralell of two Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 16. where the word importeth a deuiliſh dominion<note place="margin">Act. 8. 19. 16. 1. Pet. 5. 3.</note> and preualence; and alſo out of the 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 3. where it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a violent and fleecing gouernment. <hi>Yea but he ſhould</hi> (ſay you) <hi>haue looked backe into the old Testament of the Septuag. Sis memor ô mendax.</hi> In your quarrell about <hi>Hades,</hi> you fetch vs, to expound <hi>Hell</hi> in the Creed by, prophane writers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vſe of that word in Scripture chokes your fancie: but here the Grammarians concluding againſt you, who<note place="margin">Steph. Eraſ. &amp; alij.</note> tranſlate this place of S. <hi>Matthew, dominari in illas,</hi> not <hi>illis,</hi> expreſſing the force of the prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, now you flie to <hi>Septuag.</hi> and tranſlators muſt expound Chriſts meaning. Is this your method (farre differing from <hi>Nazianzene</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Naz. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Aug. de doct.</hi>
                  </note> to fetch a naturall expoſition from an accidentall tranſlation? euen from that, which, in many ſound Diuines iudgement, is leſſe to be allowed of, as currant for deciſion of controuerſie, then our vulgar <hi>Engliſh,</hi> againſt which you haue ſo virulently declaimed. Greatly you haue boaſted of, and<note place="margin">In ep. ad Nob.</note> much threatned theſe two places, (for euery later paperwork of yours is but a <hi>Tautology</hi> of the former) <hi>Et quid tanto dignum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horat.</note> 
                  <hi>feret hic promiſſor hiatu?</hi> The ayre thundred, the hils quaked, the earth opened, and behold a mouſe. <hi>This word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and the authoritie thereof is graunted to Adam euen in his perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:16685:17"/> Geneſ. 1. <hi>and againe attributed to Chriſt in his ſoueraintie.</hi> Pſal. 110. <hi>But neither of theſe may be ſaid to haue tyrannicall power, and rule granted them. Papae, iugulâras hominem.</hi> Giue me leaue, good Maſter <hi>Thraſo,</hi> to tickle you. <hi>Tuumne, obſecro, hoc dictum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>erat? vetus credidi.</hi> Yea but what if theſe puffed ſayles hoiſted vp, ouerthrow your owne barke, and make for the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> againſt you? haue you not (to vſe your owne words) <hi>ſpunne a fayre thred, and wouen a good cloath?</hi> For the ſoueraintie giuen to <hi>Adam</hi> ouer the earth and beaſts, was iuſtly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>viz.</hi> in breaking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clods of the one, by force<note place="margin">Tertul.</note> and violence, in cicuring and ſlaying the other with blowes and death. For though fleſh of beaſts was not eaten till after<note place="margin">Gen. 9</note> the deluge, yet man before that flood and his fall, had, by the authoritie from God in the force of this word, power ouer the beaſts both of life and death, and ſo the Hebrew word <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> ſignifieth: therfore this dominion <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to keepe the Cleargie vnder, as <hi>Adam</hi> kept the earth and beaſts, (which is rightly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) wee with S. <hi>Peter</hi> deny to Eccleſiaſticall gouernours, as forbidden by our Sauiour in<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> deteſtation of Heatheniſh rulers, who vſed their ſubiects like beaſts, both imploying them in ſeruice ſlauiſhly, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them vp either by executions or exactions. As, if your malice blinded not your knowledge, you might ſee by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 11. for God there deſcribing the manner<note place="margin">1. Sam. 8. 11.</note> of their King which ſhould raigne ouer them, he ſheweth a paterne of the Heatheniſh tyrannie, not of that lawfull and princely authoritie preſcribed by himſelfe, hauing inioyned the contrarie in the law of <hi>Moſes. Deut.</hi> 17. 20. And I take it worthie the obſeruation, that God giuing prerogatiue and ſoueraintie to <hi>Cain</hi> ouer his yonger brother <hi>dominaberis illi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 7.</note> changeth the word he vſed to <hi>Adam,</hi> which the <hi>Septuag.</hi> haue tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, this being no fit gouernment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> brother ouer a brother ſo to rule; much leſſe for fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>eir children, or Paſtors ouer their charge. Now for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>er place, <hi>Pſal</hi> 110. 2. where the father ſaith to his ſonne<note place="margin">Pſal. 110. 5.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>be thou ruler in the midſt of thine enemies.</hi> (in good ſooth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16685:18"/> I pitie thee) The whole Pſalme deſcribeth Chriſt in his full power, either raigning ouer his ſubiects, whom verſ. 3. he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>populum voluntarium,</hi> a people willingly ſubmitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto him, ruling them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. with a ſcepter of righteouſneſſe, meekly and kindly, and the time of this raigne is called <hi>dies virtutis,</hi> the day of his power: Or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing<note place="margin">Vide Flamin.</note> his enemies, and making them his footſtoole, to the ſuppreſſing of whom he hath authoritie giuen him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ouerrule them, and for that he hath <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a rod of power, verſ. 2. And the time of this domination is called <hi>dies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> furoris,</hi> or <hi>narium,</hi> the day of his wrathfull indignation, that they which will not kiſſe the ſonne as friendly ſubiects, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> and be ruled by his ſcepter, ſhould be ſubdued by the ſonne as his enemies, and bruſed in peeces with his iron rod: and this alſo, being rightly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a power in reuenge againſt vnderlings, as enemies, is forbidden the Apoſtles by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. For howſoeuer he allow them with S. <hi>Paul</hi> a rod of authoritie and correction, to keepe their Cleargie in<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> awe, yet he permits them not his rod of iron to cruſh them in peeces and make potſheards of them: becauſe their power<note place="margin">Pſal. 2. Galat. 6.</note> muſt not be in reuenge but loue, and with the ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in their correction moderation, and in their puniſhments compaſſion. And ſo the ſimpleſt may ſee, that this word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is vſed in the firſt place for a dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beaſts; and in the ſecond for a reuenging power in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of enemies; and generally, as the beſt Hebricians do<note place="margin">Vide Brixian.</note> obſerue, the originall word is alwaies vſed for <hi>dominari in,</hi> or <hi>aduerſum,</hi> a domination of hoſtilitie and violence of furie. And thus being taken in your owne grin like a <hi>Woodcocke,</hi> I diſmiſſe you for this point with aduiſe, to looke vpon your blacke legs hereafter, and downe with your traine you <hi>Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke,</hi> and ceaſe craking (crauen as thou art) of thine owne <hi>vnmatchable learning,</hi> or cackling of the vnlearnednes of thy betters: for were thy grace no better in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, then thy skill is in expounding <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thou might perchance proue more humble, and write leſſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,<note place="margin">Plato.</note>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:16685:18"/> and now I come to your <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which from <hi>Plato</hi> you haue borrowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 10.</head>
               <p>NAmely, to your admirable conceit how Chriſt deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into hell, that is, <hi>the world of ſoules.</hi> Wherein you ſtill ſhew you are a great <hi>Rabbiniſt:</hi> for this is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prouerb with them, <hi>That it is better being the head of a fox, then the tayle of a lyon:</hi> that is, the author of an addle fancie, then the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of a receiued veritie. Neither the conſent of Greeke and Latin Fathers pleaſing you, who concluded his deſcent into hell locally: nor opinion of moderne writers of his deſcent into hell on the croſſe and in his paſſion triumphantly: nor the iudgement of a middle ſort for his deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into the graue, that is, hell metaphoricall, corporally: but your heyfer, like a ſullen beaſt, (becauſe it would not be <hi>vltimus inter boues,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>primus inter aſinos</hi>) muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wander alone and chunner out an Heatheniſh conceit of <hi>deſcending into the world of ſoules poetically.</hi> The chiefe arguments hereof, according<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Nob. pag. 36. &amp; inde</note> to your cuſtome, we haue ſeene before in your epiſtle to the <hi>Nobilitie;</hi> although in this your laſt Libell you tell his <hi>Grace, that if you would handle, to the full of your knowledge, the deſcent of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">pag. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt into <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, it would be as well accepted as any thing that mans paines euer ſtudied.</hi> I am ſure you haue performed the one, for in handling it you haue ſtretched out your ſelfe with <hi>Aeſops</hi>
                  <note place="margin">AEſopus.</note> toad, <hi>vt rumpantur ilia,</hi> till you haue outſtretched your ſelfe both for modeſtie and ſenſe: of your acceptance ſmall ioy you may take, and little comfort your adherents finde, and if this bee the full ſtrength of your heyfer, ſhe is but a ſuckling. For firſt there is nothing in this malicious pamphlet of yours (ſet your railings by) but a palinody, I meane not a recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (you will neuer haue that grace) but a repetition of the very arguments which <hi>H. I.</hi> one, as it ſeemes, whom <hi>Hugh</hi> brought vp, or, as I thinke, the vanitie is ſo ſemblable, one <hi>Hugh Broughton</hi> hath vſed in a confutation of ſome Sermons
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16685:19"/> preached at <hi>Paules</hi> croſſe, and elſewhere, by a worthie and learned Prelate of this land, to whom both <hi>H. I.</hi> and <hi>H. you</hi> come as neere for found iudgement and multiplicitie of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, though, you ſay, you outſtrip him, <hi>as doth the footman to the Lydian coach,</hi> as <hi>Pindarus</hi> ſpeaketh and <hi>Plutarch</hi> applies it.<note place="margin">Pindarus, Plut. Nic.</note> So that if you were the author of that confutation, he that conferres them both will ſweare you play the <hi>Cuckow;</hi> if not, then neuer brag of your ſelfe, that you are the onely <hi>cleerer of Diuinitie,</hi> for there is not any argument in this your Libell touching <hi>Sheol</hi> and <hi>Hades</hi> out of Scripture, or out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, but there it is. And now, <hi>res non inuenta reperta eſt,</hi> wee<note place="margin">Ouid.</note> haue found a match for Maſter <hi>Broughton,</hi> both, as it ſeemes, brought vp neere <hi>Twatling ſtreete.</hi> Againe, how your worke is accepted, ſee to your ſhame and confuſion of countenance and conſcience, if this be not ſeared and that ſteeled, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of that reuerend father, of this point, in his concluſion to the reader from page 357. vnto the bookes end, where he hath killed <hi>Goliah</hi> with his owne ſword, and out of your own Poets and Philoſophers ſo learnedly and iudiciouſly hath confuted this your fooliſh paradox of the <hi>World of ſoules,</hi> that neither you will euer bee able to anſwere it, vnleſſe as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>you will adde rebellion vnto ſinne,</hi> and bee of <hi>Tully</hi> his<note place="margin">Iob. 34. 37. <hi>Tuſ. quaeſt.</hi>
                  </note> minde, <hi>cum Plaetone inſanire magis quam cum alijs recte ſentire,</hi> rather to be mad with <hi>Plato,</hi> then yeeld to the trueth of Gods ſpirit: nor any thing can bee added, which there is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently for this matter contained: ſo that I will be the ſhorter herein, as being not worthie to gleane after his harueſt, and ſpare thoſe infinite quotations out of all the Poets, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this fancie I had gathered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 11.</head>
               <p>ONly I wiſh the reader to obſerue in this your defence, as you terme it, firſt, <hi>your diſloyall blasphemie:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>your Heatheniſh diuinitie:</hi> thirdly, <hi>your abſurd and opinionatiue vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> In the firſt, challenging the Queenes moſt ſacred Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16685:19"/> with breach of her oath, charging the <hi>Defendour of the faith</hi> that ſhe aduentures her ſtate and ſoule vpon an hereſie,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Reg. pag. 12. 13.</note> and calling the whole Realme an <hi>Apostaticall land,</hi> for allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this article. It is well you carrie your pardon about you, giuen you in patent by <hi>Mania,</hi> and ſealed with the inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Laeſum cerebrum.</hi> Haſt thou forgot his counſell, who ſaid we muſt ſpeake of Princes either <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, either brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Plut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olon</note> or ſweetly? Could the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> haue ſaid more? Great thankes, you ſay, you haue euen from Papiſts for your paines and ſtudies: it is no marueile, for flyes delight not more in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries oyntments,</hi> then they doe in treaſonable ſpeeches,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10,</note> and male contented ſlanderous fugitiues. But how hath ſhe violated her oath, or the land forſaken her firſt faith? For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, ſay you, <hi>King Edward held, to which ſhee is ſworne, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">pag. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>the Realme agreed, that Chriſts ſoule neuer went to hell, or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henna</hi> in your terme, (we will ſpeake Engliſh, as taking them to be all one in the new Teſtament, and haue as good autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to thinke that <hi>Hell</hi> may bee as well deriued from <hi>Yell,</hi> or<note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Howle,</hi> as being the place of <hi>wayling and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> as from <hi>Hayle</hi> or <hi>pull,</hi> which is your coniecture.) What a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<note place="margin">pag. 5.</note> is that tongue of thine, that is not vnruly enough in reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mens perſons, but it muſt grow worſe in vntruly falſify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Acts of Parliament and articles of Synod? Reade the third article concluded in the Synod <hi>anno</hi> (as I take it) 1552. <hi>Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Art. 3. Edw. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Christus pro nobis mortuus eſt &amp; ſepultus, ita eſt etiam</hi> credendum <hi>ad Inferos deſcendiſſe, &amp;c.</hi> adding that, which we, auoyding vnwarranted curioſitie, haue left out, <hi>viz.</hi> the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note place="margin">And it is our third article, <hi>anno 62.</hi>
                  </note> of the time of his abode, the purpoſe of his deſcent, and the perſons relieued or releaſed thereby. <hi>Yea but P. Martyr and Martin Bucer who were the Pylots of the Kings religion, his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">pag. 12. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>tongue and his heart, they ſhew the Kings minde.</hi> It is well that you will at ſometimes name the parties by whom you thriue, and at whoſe trenchers you liue: for this whole tractate of yours, <hi>the marrow of your wiſedome, and the full ſtrength of your knowledge,</hi> is but the droppings of other mens taps, which, howſoeuer from them it ſauoured well, yet being coloured with the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16685:20"/> 
                  <hi>Turnſalue</hi> of your <hi>Phantasticall</hi> braine, it hath loſt both the verdure, and the vertue. <hi>Martin Bucer,</hi> indeede, ſeemeth to diſtinguiſh betweene <hi>Gehenna</hi> and <hi>Infernus,</hi> that <hi>Infernus</hi> is<note place="margin">In Matth. 27.</note> the common receptacle of good and bad, but <hi>Gehenna</hi> of the bad only: what ground he hath, let the reader iudge, I meane not to rake his aſhes, the raiſing of whoſe bones, more viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, then truly, you obiect to this our <hi>Apostaticall land,</hi> and <hi>D. Perne</hi> principally, <hi>whom you call the Archbiſhops tutor,</hi> as<note place="margin">pag. 13.</note> vaine a tradition, though nothing ſo impicus, as that of your <hi>Rabbins;</hi> who write that <hi>Sombaſſar</hi> was ſchoolemaſter vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt man that euer was. <hi>D. Perne</hi> being no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe tutor to him, chooſing him, being ſcholler of <hi>Pembroke Hall,</hi> to be fellow in <hi>Peter Houſe,</hi> then <hi>D. Hawford</hi> was to you, being fellow of <hi>Chriſts Colledge,</hi> after that <hi>Trinitie Colledge</hi> and <hi>S. Iohns</hi> had ſpued you out from their company, for a factious, proud, malepart, mad-headed, fantaſticall boy, (howſoeuer you haue boaſted otherwiſe moſt vainly in your epiſtle to the Earle of <hi>Huntington.</hi>) But to returne, albeit <hi>Bucer</hi> ſo diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh,<note place="margin">Ad Sed. Olam.</note> yet his concluſion is, that this article <hi>He deſcended into Hell,</hi> is but an explication of the former <hi>He dyed and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried,</hi> taking <hi>Hades</hi> for the graue. But, giue it ſo, that <hi>Bucer</hi> his opinion is, that the bodie being in the graue, his ſoule ioyned it ſelfe to the ſoules of the <hi>Iuſt,</hi> and ſo <hi>Infernus</hi> to ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſtate of the ſoule ſeparate from the bodie, (which opinion I am loath, too ſtraightly, for reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the dead man, to examine and rifle) yet muſt we thinke that the religious King tooke him for a <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and would tye his faith to mens perſons (which S. <hi>Iames</hi> forbids)? or ſhall wee<note place="margin">Iam. 2.</note> rather beleeue the King himſelfe, who, in the articles of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion concluded in the Clergy Synod, confirmed by the States in Parliament, and eſtabliſhed by his Royall aſſent, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auerres <hi>credendum eſt,</hi> wee muſt beleeue that Chriſts ſoule went <hi>ad Inferos,</hi> to them which were below? and this ſame ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is ſtill in force, grounded vpon Scriptures, concluded by<note place="margin">Art. 3. anno 62.</note> the reuerend Synod, and promulgated by her Maieſties au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and conſent, for the faith of the whole Realme, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16685:20"/> to which your ſelfe haue ſubſcribed, or elſe you are an Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and came in at the window. And now let any reader iudge (though otherwiſe he knew thee not) of your braine and vaine, who not only chargeſt the Lords annoynted with breach of her oath, in print, in a Libell, from a forraine coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, (an inſolence ſeuerely puniſhable in an obiection of trueth) but alſo blaſphemeſt her moſt ſacred Maieſtie in moſt beaſtly reſemblances, not to bee named; and vpbraideſt her<note place="margin">pag. 71. lin. 7. pag. 12. &amp; Epiſt. ad Reg.</note> religious ſoule with periurie, in an article of faith, and a great point of religion, and that moſt vntruly. If you pleade your Patent (aboue named) leaue <hi>Baſil</hi> and returne to <hi>Bedlem,</hi> if not, but you will needes perſwade vs you are in your wits, it is pitie (becauſe you are ſuch a Grecian) but the Greeken ſhould end your period.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 12.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond thing is your <hi>Heatheniſh Diuinitie,</hi> in making <hi>Hell</hi> into which our Sauiour deſcended, to bee nothing but that <hi>Platonicall</hi> and <hi>Plutonicall Hades</hi> of the Heathen, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning the <hi>Creede</hi> to be iudged by a Conſiſtorie of Painims for proper phraſe. You will not allow <hi>Galen</hi> the prince of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions<note place="margin">pag. 9.</note> to expound <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88. 11. but recourſe muſt be had to the Hebrew, euen to a falſe roote, to cloake a ſlip which the <hi>Septuag.</hi> there made, but here the prince of Poets muſt mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the act, and interprete the action of the prince of our ſaluation. So true a difference is that which ſome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue made betweene <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a light fancie, and a ſetled iudgement, that this is <hi>ſenſus elatus ê ſcripturis:</hi> but that is <hi>ſenſus allatus ad ſcripturas.</hi> It was the greateſt ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie that Iſrael felt, when they were forced to goe downe to their deadly foes the Philiſtines to ſharpen their axes, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks<note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.</note> and inſtruments of husbandrie (for they were wholly deformed of their weapons) and a ſorer vaſſalage muſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity indure, if her profeſſion muſt be made good by Poets fictions. Strange fire to be offered on Gods altar was ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Leuit. 10.</note>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16685:21"/> puniſhed, * becauſe as from heauen it came, ſo in the firſt<note place="margin">Leuit. 9.</note> nature it muſt be preſerued. Yea your owne Pagans were in that point ſo religious, that they counted it vnlawfull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh the <hi>Vestall fire,</hi> being by ſome ſtrange miſhap extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed,<note place="margin">Plut. Num.</note> with any materiall fire and prophane, but a deuiſe was inuented to kindle it from heauen by the Sunne. Surely leſſe lawfull is it, becauſe more diſhonorable to Gods glorie, and the dignitie of Chriſtian profeſſion, to make the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, who account the preaching of the Goſpell follie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounders<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> of Chriſtian oracles, and to fetch light from their Heatheniſh <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> for the illuſtration of diuine myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The rule of the holy Ghoſt being, as his method is, <hi>to compare ſpirituall things with ſpirituall things,</hi> and leaue the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> man to things within his capacitie, becauſe the ſpirit of the Prophets is ſubiect to, &amp; muſt be iudged by Prophets. For<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> who knoweth not, that Chriſtianity hath vſed many words in ſeuerall ſence from the common phraſe? Is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the new Teſtament to be meaſured by the Athenians modell? or <hi>fides</hi> by the Romanes? who notwithſtanding made ſo reuerend ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt thereof, as that they thought her a <hi>Goddeſſe,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted<note place="margin">Plut. Num.</note> the oath <hi>per fidem</hi> to bee the greateſt and moſt ſacred? S. <hi>Iohns</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one of the moſt eſſentiall names of the ſecond<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> perſon in Trinitie, doth it import no more, nor ſignifie any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing then the Orators <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the Poets <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>? And though <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Hermes</hi> haue plumbd it deeply, muſt wee<note place="margin">Plato. Hermes.</note> reach no further, then their ſhallow ſounding? So <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing properly among the Fathers and Councels vſed for the incarnation of our Sauiour, how farre differeth it from that fence which in Paganiſh writers is rife and vſuall? And if for<note place="margin">Theodoretus in Polym.</note> 
                  <hi>Hades</hi> in the <hi>Creede</hi> wee muſt bee tried by Poets, why in the ſame <hi>Symbole</hi> are not we to be iudged by them, for him, whom both we, and they call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Father almightie? Did the Apoſtle, citing the halfe verſe out of <hi>Aratus,</hi> apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> it to our God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, referre them that heard him to their <hi>Iupiter,</hi> of whom the Poet ſpake it, and ſo make vs the progenie of their <hi>Laſciuious Stallion,</hi> of whom <hi>Clem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Clem.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:16685:21"/> writeth, that which <hi>Suetonius</hi> doth of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that he was euery<note place="margin">Sueton. lul.</note> mans woman &amp; euery womans man? The reaſon is al one. For by the Poets figments <hi>Hades</hi> was <hi>Iupiters</hi> brother both ſonnes to <hi>Saturne:</hi> and ſo, by your owne iudges, the penner of the <hi>Creede,</hi> when he ſaid that Chriſt <hi>deſcended</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, meant that he went into the houſe of <hi>Hades,</hi> who was gouernour of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour parts, as <hi>Iupiter</hi> of the ayre, and <hi>Neptune</hi> of the ſea. For<note place="margin">Homerus, &amp; Heſiodus, &amp; Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Poets is no name of place, but figuratiuely. But for this diſcourſe you may be referred to that concluſion of the right <hi>Reuerend Father</hi> in the place before named, to which nothing can be added for learning or ſubſtance in this point; where he hath ſhewed both your ſelfe and <hi>H. I.</hi> to bee but queſting puppies, for all your wide mouthes. Yet one thing I cannot omit, that men may ſee (which thy ſelfe will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) how you, the <hi>ſole true calculator of times and ages,</hi> haue forgot your ſelfe: for labouring to bring all Scripture words to Poets phraſe, you wil needs perſwade vs that S. <hi>Peter,</hi> vſing thoſe words of torment <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, borrowed them all<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 4.</note> from <hi>Homer</hi> and his <hi>proſe commentary.</hi> Firſt, for <hi>Homer,</hi> what proofe haue you of S. <hi>Peters</hi> reading him? S. <hi>Peter</hi> could tell<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> you that no Scripture is of any priuate mans motion, but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie men ſpeake as the ſpirit moueth them, becauſe all Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> inſpired of God. Wee laugh at the Canon gloſſe for ſaying that S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7. alluded to that verſe in <hi>Ouid, Odero ſi potero, ſi non, inuitus amab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And ſurely, lighting<note place="margin">Ouid.</note> vpon this and ſuch like ſtuffe in your fardle of fancies, I ſay with <hi>Horace, -vt mihi ſaepe Bilem, ſaepe iocum vestri mouêre tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horat. epiſt.</note> Laughter and anger haue ſtrouen within mee which ſhould preuaile, laughter verely, but that it is in ſuch ſerious matter. But by as good reaſon you may ſay that Chriſt our Sauiour had read <hi>Pindarus,</hi> becauſe, ſpeaking to perſecuting <hi>Saul</hi> out of heauen, he vſed the very words of the Poet <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Pind. Pyth. od. 2.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>it is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks.</hi> Mary that he<note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> ſhould reade his <hi>proſe commentary,</hi> if it be <hi>Eustathius,</hi> as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by your booke <hi>pag.</hi> 63. (vnleſſe you haue got ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16685:22"/> in a wall, as you did the <hi>Septuag.</hi> vnheard of) that is worth the obſeruing. It is coniectured by the workes of <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> and ſome of the Poets, that they haue read<note place="margin">Serranus.</note> the bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that Scripture which was before their time, at leaſt, in their trauaile, had conference with ſuch as informed them therein; but that the Apoſtle ſhould reade a commentarie before the author was borne, is more then prophecie. S. <hi>Ierome</hi> out of an oration of <hi>Tully</hi> not extant, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth<note place="margin">Tul. pro Q. Gall.</note> a place where a certaine Poet bringeth in <hi>Euripides</hi> and <hi>Menander, Socrates</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> dialoguiſing and conferring together, who liued in times different <hi>non annis, ſed ſaeculis,</hi> and therefore thinketh the abſurditie ſo ridiculous, that it deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth<note place="margin">Hieron.</note> a ſupploſion or an hiſſing: and is not this as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the vntrueth) that S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould fetch his phraſes from a Biſhop not borne many yeeres after? But thus you bewray your ſelfe a notable ſcholler of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> whoſe propertie is, as <hi>Caluin</hi> well obſerueth, <hi>vt diuinent hoc &amp; illud ſine delectu</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calu. in Hab. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; pudore.</hi> And if you aske them a reaſon, their anſwer is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, <hi>We thinke ſo.</hi> Yet this ouerſight may be ſmiled at, but that<note place="margin">in Nah. 1.</note> which followes procures deteſtation. <hi>Dauids</hi> ſinnes, though great, did not ſo haſten-on Gods iudgements, as that by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.</note> he had cauſed the enemies of the Lord to blaſpheme; neither is it your ſtrange diuinitie that procures our indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, becauſe wee know it is but the franticke <hi>delirium</hi> of one, whoſe pride hath made him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. but this is<note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> it which grieues vs, and ſhould confound you, that both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt and Pagan hath hereby iuſt cauſe of ſcandall. Some of the firſt ſort, alreadie, for ſpeeches farre more differing from<note place="margin">Roſſaeus &amp; Reynoldus.</note> any vicinitie to prophanenes then this of yours, (though moſt ſlanderouſly) haue ſet out whole Libels in which they would demonſtrate, that the opinions of Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are more deteſtable then Heathens, and particularly, that <hi>Caluiniſme</hi> is worſe then <hi>Paganiſme.</hi> What may they ſay now (I am ſorie <hi>Broughton,</hi> to giue them this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but onely to ſhew, how thy proud malice, to glorifie thy ſelfe, cares not to diſgrace
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16685:22"/> both men and religion) when they ſhal reade and heare, that among vs it is defended and printed, that Chriſt went into the Poets <hi>Hades,</hi> that is, at the beſt into the <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſpirits of their <hi>Hector</hi> and <hi>Achilles?</hi> Beſides the occaſion giuen the Pagans to ſtumble, and blaſphemouſly to ſay <hi>Where is now their God?</hi> when they ſhall ſhew that more honour is by them attributed to their Idols and greater feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, then by ſome of vs to our Sauiour: for they tranſlate thoſe great ones, whom they deifie, immediatly into heauen, as we may ſee of <hi>Romulus</hi> in <hi>Liuy,</hi> and of <hi>Augustus</hi> in <hi>Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sueto. Aug.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And <hi>Homer</hi> preſents vnto <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> being in <hi>Hades,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the force and ſtrength of <hi>Hercules</hi> a ghoſt, but <hi>Hercules</hi> himſelfe was confeſſed to be in heauen with their immortall Gods. But it pleaſeth you to leaue our Sauiour in <hi>Hades</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day, a place by their owne confeſſion, as we ſhall ſee anone, at the beſt, of no ſolace nor delight. But our Sauiour<note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> his ſpeech is true, that there is no expecting of grapes from thornes, or figges from thiſtles, nor from an addle head good deuiſe, nor ſound diuinitie from a giddie, brainſicke, pride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwolne companion, that, to feede his owne ſelfe-pleaſing humour, cares not to bring all religion into that olde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Eraſ. &amp; Iun. us.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECTIO. 13.</head>
               <p>YOur opinionatiue vanitie is the laſt, that Chriſts <hi>deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into Hell,</hi> is nothing elſe, <hi>but he aſcended into heauen.</hi> It is reported of <hi>Polemo</hi> the Sophiſter, that being at <hi>Smyrna</hi> a<note place="margin">Rhod. lib. 20.</note> ſpectatour of a Tragedie, a ridiculous actor comes out vpon the ſtage, and his part being to pronounce <hi>O coelum,</hi> he bends his eyes and hands to the earth; and anone crying out <hi>O ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> his hands and eyes were lifted vp to heauen: away flings the Sophiſter and cries out vpon him, This fellow, ſaith he, hath made a <hi>Solaeciſme</hi> with his hands. It may well agree with a turbulent ſpirit <hi>Coelum terra miſcere,</hi> but to confound
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16685:23"/> heauen and hell, and make aſcending and deſcending to bee all one, is not only a <hi>Solaeciſme</hi> in Diuinitie, but euen in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon, which hath concluded <hi>ſurſum</hi> and <hi>deorſum</hi> to be<note place="margin">Ariſt. de Coelo.</note> 
                  <hi>Oppoſita.</hi> In the Poets <hi>Hades,</hi> the two paſſages were leuelled (as I may ſay) vpon one floore, the one leading into <hi>Elyſium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plato. Virgil.</note> the other into <hi>Tartarus:</hi> the firſt, the place of the beſt mens ſoules: the laſt, of torment, for the worſt. But as S. <hi>Luke</hi> (who muſt direct Chriſtians) deſcribes it, <hi>Hades,</hi> the place of <hi>Diue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> torment, was below, and <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, the reſt of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> was aboue, and betweene them both a great huge <hi>Hiatus</hi> making them <hi>mutually inacceſſible.</hi> And <hi>Eliah</hi> being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way<note place="margin">2. Reg. 2. Num. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>was caried vp</hi> into heauen: but <hi>Core</hi> and his companie <hi>went downe</hi> aliue into <hi>Sheol.</hi> And <hi>Lucifer</hi> with his angels being ſeated in heauen, were throwne downe (ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. Iude ep.</note> 
                  <hi>Iude</hi>) into the pit of darknes. The trueth is, reade whoſoeuer will (let him not bee paradoxically preiudicious) the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Poets, he ſhall neuer finde <hi>Sheol</hi> of the Hebrewes, nor <hi>Hades</hi> of the Greekes, (one place in <hi>Plato</hi> excepted, which the <hi>Reuerend Father</hi> hath notably illuded) but at the beſt it is an irkſome, mirkſome deepe place, and moſt-what oppoſite to heauen. Elſe, neither would Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. haue<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>reioyced</hi> that his ſoule ſhould not bee left in <hi>Sheol,</hi> if either he bee there ſtill, as by your diuinitie he is; or if it bee a place of reſt and happines, as your fancifull opinion conceiues it: nor <hi>Achilles</hi> in <hi>Homer</hi> would haue wiſhed to be any ſwaines pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> vpon earth in the greateſt want, rather then the prince of ſoules in <hi>Hades,</hi> as to <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> he proteſts. But let me aske thee, good <hi>Sir Hugh,</hi> (though naturals for the moſt part loue not to anſwere queſtions) is Chriſt now in <hi>Sheol</hi> or <hi>Hades</hi> where he was preſently after his paſſion? he is, ſay you: that is, at the right hand of his father, in whoſe preſence are the Saints departed ſinging <hi>Alleluiah?</hi> Yes, ſay you. Now then, ſhew vs any one place in the Bible for <hi>Sheol,</hi> or in the Poets for <hi>Hades,</hi> where either of them are put for Heauen or Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice: or in any ſacred or prophane writer, where going
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16685:23"/> downe is put for going vp? The contrary of both wee ſhew. <hi>If I climbe vp to heauen,</hi> thou art there; <hi>if I goe downe to Sheol,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 139. Matth. 11.</note> thou art there alſo. And thou <hi>Capernaum art exalted</hi> to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſhalt bee <hi>brought downe</hi> to <hi>Hades.</hi> Yea by your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 19. the Heauens are <hi>high, Sheol</hi> is <hi>deepe,</hi> and that which <hi>Iob,</hi> ſay you, would haue called <hi>Sheol,</hi> God himſelfe cals <hi>Death.</hi> So that <hi>Sheol,</hi> at the beſt, either is not Heauen, as you often auouch, or elſe there is a third place beſides Heauen and Hell called <hi>Sheol</hi> for the Saints to reſt in. But what man of ſenſe would talke ſencibly to a <hi>Dottrell,</hi> being one of thoſe Diuines, whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribeth, ſo ignorantly raſh, that they know not what they ſay, nor whereof they affirme?<note place="margin">1. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLVSIO.</head>
               <p>ANd therefore I will leaue you, Maſter <hi>Broughton,</hi> with this counſell of <hi>Horace,</hi> if you will vouchſafe it, -<hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctent fabrilia fabri,</hi> returne to your <hi>Genealogies,</hi> wherein your<note place="margin">Horatius.</note> grace is beſt: for if you enter into points of faith, being out of your element, you detect your ignorance: and being both a Chriſtian and a Diuine, learne S. <hi>Pauls</hi> leſſon, <hi>in meekenes of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philip. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>minde to eſteeme others better then your ſelfe.</hi> But eſpeciallie, which is the frequent compariſon of the Fathers, leaue that dogged humour, furiouſly to runne at the ſtone, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the flinger: for howſoeuer you charge the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> (which iealous ſuſpition of yours hath cauſed all this gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyle) as the chiefe hinderer of your preferment, yet looke vp to God, who hath a principall ſtroke in all theſe actions. He hath made beaſts to excell men in ſenſes, but he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied<note place="margin">Plutarchus.</note> them reaſon. The Oſtrich he hath framed a goodly bird with feathers and wings, <hi>Iob.</hi> 39. 16. but he hath depriued her<note place="margin">Iob. 39. 16. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of wiſedome, and giuen her no vnderſtanding, verſ. 20. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you he hath giuen great ornaments, of learning &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but he hath denied you diſcretion, which is as the brine
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16685:24"/> that ſeaſons learning, &amp; the eſpeciall helpe in a place of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which you ſo affect. For as Sacrifices, in the law, not<note place="margin">Leuit. 2.</note> ſalted were vnacceptable; ſo religion, without diſcretion, is vnſauourie; and learning, without iudgement, ſiniſter and raſh; and gouernment, without wiſedome, proud and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. The aduancers of learned men are taught a precept, by a prouerb, <hi>Ne puero gladium,</hi> not to giue ſwords to childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Cicero. Plato.</note> but you Grecians, ſaith <hi>Solon,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are alwaies children. And you, Maſter <hi>Broughton,</hi> that arrogate to your ſelfe the <hi>Attick Science,</hi> haue ſhewed your ſelfe a childe in all your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and therefore by <hi>Aristotle</hi> his rule, (becauſe it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) vnfit to bee a Diuine, much more a ruler among Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines. Deſire not to bee a <hi>cleerer</hi> of S. <hi>Peter</hi> rather then his hearer, who wils you to humble your ſelfe vnder Gods migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> hand, and ſubmit your ſelfe to all your ſuperiours (not as you take them, but as God hath placed them): ſo ſhall you be thankfull to your creator, loyall to your betters, charitable in your affections, temperate in your ſpeeches, moderate in your furie, retentiue of your ſlaunders, and leſſe ſelfe-boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of your great ſufficiencies, remembring what both your ſelfe haue written to the Nobilitie of <hi>England</hi> that, to bring a<note place="margin">pag. 43.</note> good thing to paſſe by perſwaſion in writing, ſhould neede a <hi>milde ſtile:</hi> and alſo that of S. <hi>Paul, that he which praiſeth himſelf</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>is not allowed, but he whom the Lord praiſeth. Nam lauda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do te bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fis malus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Austen.</hi> But in any caſe take out <hi>Pythagoras</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtinus. Pythag.</note> precept, <hi>Piſſe not againſt the Sun:</hi> ceaſe ſo fondly &amp; ſenceleſly to vpbraid with vnlearnednes &amp; want of conſcience that moſt <hi>Reuerend Father</hi> and right worthie Prelate of our Church, whom his place and vertues (euen by Philoſophy) haue made<note place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from ſuch an one as thy ſelfe, who may be thy maſter for ſound learning and humilitie. Of whom I would ſpeak more, but that I know to his <hi>Grace</hi> it is a burden, and from mee it would be accompted flatterie. For if I liſt, or it were needfull to gather (as thou haſt done of thy ſelfe more buſily then truly) what both ſtrangers, and the beſt learned among vs,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16685:24"/> haue in print written of him, both by report, and of certaine knowledge, to his perpetuall praiſe, for his ſound iudgement in learning, his ſincere conſcience in his actions, and his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable mildnes in his deportment, I might fill a volume to thy confuſion; but as <hi>Philo</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Philo</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Trueth is the alſufficient commendation,</hi> and when enuie hath burſt her guts, and ſlaunder crackt her lungs, his fame ſhall found; they that liue with him loue him, they that know him reuerence him, they which heare of him admire him; vnleſſe they bee either diſcontedly malicious, or ſchiſmatically fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, or paradoxically furious. It is not too late to recall your ſelf, and to craue pardon of his <hi>Grace,</hi> whom thus againſt thine owne conſcience, and all trueth thou haſt ſo intolerably abuſed, that ſo as <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaith, <hi>qui primas non habuiſti ſapientiae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug Retract.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecundas habeas partes modestiae,</hi> ſince thou ſeeſt thy ſelfe to want wiſedome in all thy actions, others may ſee that thou haſt modeſtie in this repentance. Otherwiſe, if you continue as you haue begun, you will be counted among wiſe men, as now you are, the Maſter of abſurdities; the mintmaſter of fancies; a Phariſaicall herauld ſounding your owne praiſes; a ſottiſh <hi>Pygmalion</hi> enamoured with your owne deuiſes; an <hi>Aenigmaticall</hi> ridler writing without ſenſe; an opprobrious <hi>Therſites</hi> inſulting without modeſtie, reuiling without reaſon, rauing without meaſure. Your bookes but ſquibs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds of gunpowder and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, making more ſtinke then ſtirre, and yet more ſtirre then hurt; the mirrour of vanitie; the refuſe of Diuinitie; the quinteſſence of follie; <hi>Phoebus</hi> curtaines enueloped with oracles; <hi>Aegyptians</hi> cups reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with coniectures, embeliſhed with ſlaunders. And ſo I end with that ſalutation which King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cedon</hi> gaue to mad <hi>Menecrates,</hi> as vaine a Phiſition in the opinion of his facultie, as you are for your Diuinitie, (intituling himſelfe <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiſhing you a ſound mind in a healthfull bodie: for verely ſooner you had receiued an anſwere, but that the rumour was here with vs that you were dead: but that was
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16685:25"/> checkt, and then it was rife that you were proued mad: but I hope better for your ſoules ſake, and it will bee better for your names ſake, if you can be humble.</p>
               <closer>Tuus ſis &amp; ero.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Some faults eſcaped thus to be corrected.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>affection</hi> reade <hi>affectation.</hi> pag. 8. lin. 8. <hi>Sappho</hi> reade <hi>Pſappho.</hi> pag. 11. lin. 19. <hi>F.</hi> put <hi>ff.</hi> marg. pag. 13. lin. <hi>penult.</hi> and ſo pa. 16. marg. lin. 4. auering <hi>reade</hi> auerring. pag. 17. lin. 13. Iac. 18. <hi>marg.</hi> put Luc. 18. pag. 21. lin. 11. 1. Tit. 6. <hi>marg.</hi> put 1. Tim. 6. pag. 23. lin. 20.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="comparison">
            <pb facs="tcp:16685:25"/>
            <head>A COMPARISON OF CERTAINE VAINE SPEE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHES OF HVGH BROVGHTON, with thoſe of <hi>Pyrgopolinices Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> his glorious Souldier.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Broughton.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Miles Glor.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>D. Reynolds</hi> nor <hi>D. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> may or will incounter me.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cum quo</hi> bellator Mars <hi>haud auſit congredi, Ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> aequipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare ſuas virtutes ad meas.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Iewes deſired to haue me ſent to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Synagogues in Conſtantinople, if it were but <hi>to ſee</hi> my Angelicall countenance.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Molestae ſunt, accedunt, orant, obſecrant</hi> videre vt liceat, <hi>ad ſeſe accerſi iubent.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Zurick, Denmarke, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, French, Dutch, Papiſt, Proteſtant, Lutherans, Iewes call for me, <hi>being a man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued ouer the world.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nam itae me occurſant multae, haud meminiſſe omnes poſſum;</hi> tanta miſeria eſt hominem eſſe pulchrum nimis.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>No Biſhop nor Baron ſhall be <hi>my</hi> Lord, <hi>the Queene only</hi> is fit to be <hi>my</hi> Patrone.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nam ad</hi> meam <hi>formam</hi> illa vna <hi>digna eſt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The LL. ſaid that <hi>I</hi> was <hi>nulli ſecundus</hi> for knowledge and learning.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Magnum</hi> me <hi>faciam nunc, quoniam</hi> illi me <hi>collaudâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>D. R.</hi> ſayd there was as much in <hi>Br.</hi> as could bee <hi>in a man.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Heus dignior fuit</hi> quiſquam homo <hi>qui eſſet?</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16685:26"/>If the Queene will not <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre</hi> me for my paines, I will leaue the land.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Niſi huic verri</hi> affertur mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hic ſeminio ſuo quam<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> porculonam partituru'ſt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>They ſent a meſſenger for <hi>me,</hi> as though <hi>I were a man</hi> fit to bee cited by ſuch fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Permirum ecastor praedicas te adiſſe at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> exorâſſe</hi> per epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolam aut nuncium; <hi>Quaſi regem adiri hunc aiunt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I requeſted his <hi>Grace</hi> to tel <hi>D. C.</hi> that <hi>I was his better by Heroaldie.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Neſcio an tu hoc ex me audie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris an non,</hi> Nepos ſum Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Queene <hi>ſo much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemes of me,</hi> that, ſhe ſaid, ſhe would not for all the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the world <hi>I</hi> ſhould be diſcontented.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nulli mortalium ſcio obtigiſſe hoc niſi duobus,</hi> mihi <hi>&amp; Phao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Leſbio,</hi> Tam nimiè vt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maremur.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I returned anſwere that <hi>I</hi> would no longer ſerue her Maieſtie, if I were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced <hi>for my ſtudies out of hand.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nam quid ego hic asto</hi> tantiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cum hac forma &amp; fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis? ſic fruſtror?</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <head>Plautus.</head>
               <l>Leuiorem hoc homine ſi quis vnquam viderit,</l>
               <l>Aut gloriarum pleniorem, quàm illic eſt:</l>
               <l>Me ſibi habeto, &amp; ego me illi mancupi dabo.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16685:26"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
